We're here with our final guest lecturer for the course.
우리는 이번 강좌의 마지막 초청 강사와 함께 있습니다.
And today, we have Dr. Yunzhu Li.
오늘은 Dr. Yunzhu Li입니다.
He is an assistant professor of computer science
그는 콜롬비아 대학교의 컴퓨터
at Columbia University, where he leads the Robotic Perception,
과학 조교수로, 로봇 인식, 상호작용 및 학습 연구실을
Interaction, and Learning Lab.
이끌고 있습니다.
He is also a former instructor of CS231N,
그는 모든 초청 강사들처럼 CS231N의
like all of our guest lecturers.
이전 강사이기도 합니다.
And he taught the course in 2023 while he completed his postdoc
그는 2023년에 스탠포드에서 Fei-Fei Li 교수와 Jiajun Wu
here at Stanford with professors Fei-Fei Li and Jiajun Wu.
교수와 함께 포스트닥을 수행하면서 이 강좌를 가르쳤습니다.
His research lies at the intersection
그의 연구는 로봇 공학,
of robotics, computer vision, and machine learning.
컴퓨터 비전 및 기계 학습의 교차점에 있습니다.
And specifically, his work focuses on robot learning
특히 그의 연구는 로봇 학습에 중점을 두고 있으며,
and aims to significantly expand robots' perception
로봇의 인식 및 물리적 상호작용 능력을 크게
and physical interaction capabilities.
확장하는 것을 목표로 하고 있습니다.
In today's lecture, he'll be discussing exactly that,
오늘 강의에서는 바로 그 주제인 로봇 학습에
topic robot learning.
대해 논의할 것입니다.
And I'll now hand it off to Yunzhu for today's lecture.
이제 오늘 강의를 위해 Yunzhu에게 넘기겠습니다.
Yeah, thank you, Dean, for the very kind introduction.
네, 친절한 소개에 감사드립니다, Dean.
I'm super excited to be here.
여기 오게 되어 매우 기쁩니다.
The last time I was here giving lectures
제가 마지막으로 여기에서 강의를
was two years ago, 2023.
했던 것은 2년 전, 2023년이었습니다.
And similar, lately, I was going through many of the lectures.
최근에 많은 강의를 살펴보았습니다.
And today, I'm going to be talking about some of the things
오늘은 제가 작업해온 몇 가지에 대해
that I have been working on.
이야기할 것입니다.
And it's also a very coherent piece
그리고 이는 컴퓨터 비전을 위한 딥러닝의
of this overall picture on deep learning for computer vision.
전체 그림과 매우 일관된 부분입니다.
And this is specifically on robot learning.
이것은 로봇 학습에 관한 것입니다.
So I'll be discussing what are some
로봇이 물리적 세계를
of the interesting considerations
더 잘 인식하고 상호작용할
especially in enabling the robots to better perceive
수 있도록 하는 흥미로운 고려사항과
and interact with the physical world
이러한 고려사항이
and how some of the considerations
전형적인 컴퓨터 비전
might be different from some typical computer vision tasks
작업 및 방법과 어떻게 다를 수
and computer vision methods.
있는지에 대해 논의할 것입니다.
So first of all, you guys have already
우선, 여러분은 이미 감독
learned a lot about supervised learning.
학습에 대해 많은 것을 배웠습니다.
The scene and the setup for supervised learning
감독 학습의 장면과 설정은 데이터
is that you have data x and y.
x와 y가 있다는 것입니다.
X is the input, and y is the label.
x는 입력이고, y는 레이블입니다.
And you are trying to learn a mapping that maps from the input
입력 x에서 출력 y로 매핑하는 방법을
x to the output y.
배우려고 합니다.
There are examples you have already learned,
여러분이 이미 배운
like classification, regression, object detection, et cetera.
예로는 분류, 회귀, 객체 탐지 등이 있습니다.
And you have also learned about self-supervised learning, where
여러분은 레이블이 없는 데이터로
instead of having labels, in this case,
작업하는 자기 감독
you are just having the data without any labels.
학습에 대해서도 배웠습니다.
What you are trying to do is you come up
여기서 여러분이 하려는
with learning algorithms that is able to extract or identify
것은 보조 손실을 설계하거나 작업하여 데이터의
the underlying hidden structures of the data,
기본 숨겨진 구조를 추출하거나
just by working or designing some auxiliary loss.
식별할 수 있는 학습 알고리즘을 만드는 것입니다.
Some typical examples, including autoencoders, and there's
자동 인코더를 포함한 몇 가지 전형적인
many other examples in trying to do unsupervised learning
예가 있으며, 이 방대한 양의 레이블 없는
or self-supervised learning on top
데이터에서 비감독 학습 또는 자기 감독
of this mass amount of unlabeled data.
학습을 시도하는 다른 많은 예가 있습니다.
And the special thing and the unique things
로봇 학습의 특별한 점은
about robot learning is that the robot
로봇이 세계와
has to make physical interactions that make
상호작용하는 물리적 상호작용을
interactions with the world.
해야 한다는 것입니다.
So it's not just you have the input and outputs
단순히 입력과 출력이 있고 입력 x에서
and mapping from the input x to y
y로 매핑하거나 어떤 종류의
or some kind of latent representations.
잠재 표현이 있는 것이 아닙니다.
It's really about you are influenced
환경의 진화에 영향을
evolutions of the environments.
미치는 것입니다.
So no matter what action you decide
여러분이 실제 세계에서
to take in the real world, the world
어떤 행동을 결정하든, 그
will change as a result of that actions.
행동의 결과로 세계는 변화할 것입니다.
And the world will give you some kind of new observations
그리고 세계는 여러분에게 새로운 관찰이나
or reward telling you how the thing--
보상을 제공하여 환경이 어떻게 변화했는지,
how the environment has been changing
특정 작업을 수행하는
and how good you are in executing certain tasks.
데 얼마나 잘하고 있는지를 알려줄 것입니다.
So the goal is trying to actually come up
목표는 환경으로부터 피드백을
with a sequence of actions with feedback from the environments,
받아 보상을 극대화하거나 비용을 최소화하는
that is, to maximize some reward or minimize some cost.
일련의 행동을 실제로 고안하는 것입니다.
And robot learning, especially in the recent years,
로봇 학습, 특히 최근 몇 년 동안,
has attracted significant attention both within academia
학계와 산업 모두에서 상당한 주목을
and also within industries.
받고 있습니다.
So we have seen many startup companies and including,
그래서 우리는 많은 스타트업 회사들을 보았고, 예를 들어 테슬라
for example, physical intelligence like Tesla bots
봇이나 피규어와 같은 물리적 지능을
or Figure.
포함하고 있습니다.
They are producing those very seemingly very nice and fancy
그들은 셔츠 접기, 커피콩 조작, 또는 실제 물리적
videos of robots doing a wide range of very complicated tasks,
세계에서 흥미로운 작업을 수행하는 인간 소음과
like folding shirts, like manipulating coffee beans,
같은 매우 복잡한 작업을
or trying to have this human noise, like doing
수행하는 로봇의 멋지고
interesting tasks in the real physical world.
화려한 비디오를 제작하고 있습니다.
So this field, like I mentioned, has attracted a lot of attention
그래서 제가 언급했듯이 이 분야는 많은 주목과
and also a lot of investments.
투자도 받고 있습니다.
Here are just some examples of some recent startups
여기 최근 로봇 학습 분야에서 막대한
in the field of robot learnings that
투자를 유치하고 있는
is able to attract a huge amount of investments, trying
스타트업의 몇 가지 예가 있습니다. 이들은
to build this general purpose robots
환경과 물리적 상호작용을 할
that can make physical interactions
수 있는 범용 로봇을
with the environments.
만들려고 합니다.
So obviously, not only those startups, mainly
따라서 분명히 이러한 스타트업뿐만 아니라,
big established companies are also having their own robotics
주로 큰 기존 회사들도 자신들의 로봇 조사와
investigations and initiatives, trying
이니셔티브를 가지고 있으며,
to develop their own general purpose robots
환경과의 범용적이고
that is able to make general purpose and high performance
고성능의 물리적 상호작용을 할 수 있는
physical interactions with the environment.
범용 로봇을 개발하려고 하고 있습니다.
So for today's lectures, I'm going
오늘 강의에서는 로봇
to give you some kind of overviews
학습의 현재 성공과 붐을
on some of the key techniques enabling
가능하게 하는 주요 기술적
factors of the current success and boom of robot learnings.
요소에 대한 개요를 제공할 것입니다.
We will start with problem formulations.
문제 정의부터 시작하겠습니다.
How can we more concretely define
우리가 구축해온 문제를 더 구체적으로 어떻게
the problems we have been building,
정의할 수 있을까요? 그리고
and how can we formally think about the robust interactions
환경과의 강력한 상호작용에 대해 어떻게 공식적으로
with the environments?
생각할 수 있을까요?
So I will then discuss the more perception side.
그럼 더 인식 측면에 대해 논의하겠습니다.
I will talk about the different considerations
로봇이 환경을 인식하는 방식과
between how robots perceive the environments
사람들이 일반적으로 컴퓨터
and how people typically consider in the computer vision
비전 커뮤니티에서 고려하는 방식의
community and what's special about robots' perception,
차이점, 그리고 로봇 인식의 특별한
now talking about reinforcement learning, model
점에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
learning, model-based planning, imitation learning, also
강화 학습, 모델 학습, 모델 기반 계획,
some of the recent trends on robotic foundation models
모방 학습, 최근 로봇 기초 모델에
and also using the remaining time to discuss
대한 트렌드와 여유 시간을 사용하여 우리가
some of the challenges we still see lies ahead of us.
여전히 직면하고 있는 도전 과제에 대해 논의하겠습니다.
So we'll start with problem formulation.
문제 정의부터 시작하겠습니다.
So this is, in general, how the problem
일반적으로 문제는 이렇게 보여야
should look like, at least in a graphical illustration.
하며, 최소한 그래픽적으로는 이렇게 표현됩니다.
So in the middle, we have this agent.
가운데에 에이전트가 있습니다.
The agent is given some task objective.
에이전트는 어떤 작업 목표를 부여받습니다.
This task objective could be, for example, language
이 작업 목표는 예를 들어 인간의
instructions from human or some kind of objective functions
언어 지시사항이나 이 에이전트가 특정 작업을 수행하는
measuring how good this agent is in doing some specific task.
데 얼마나 잘하고 있는지를 측정하는 어떤 목표 함수일 수 있습니다.
This agent is taking states from the physical world
이 에이전트는 물리적 세계나 어떤 환경에서
or some kind of environments.
상태를 가져옵니다.
And the agent decides what action to take,
그리고 에이전트는 물리적
like this at here, that needs to be
세계에서 실행해야 할
executed in the physical world.
행동을 결정합니다.
And this physical world will be updated and given
이 물리적 세계는 업데이트되고 이 상태의 st+1과
this state's st plus 1, as well as
보상이 주어져 에이전트에게
the rewards, telling the agents how good it is doing its task.
작업 수행이 얼마나 잘 되고 있는지를 알려줍니다.
So this is how the framework in general looks like.
이것이 일반적으로 프레임워크가 어떻게 생겼는지입니다.
So you have to be very clear on this type of formulation that
목표, 상태, 행동 및 보상으로 구성된 이러한
consists of goal, states, actions, and also rewards.
유형의 정의를 매우 명확히 해야 합니다.
That specifically defines the problems of the robot learning
로봇 학습 시나리오의 문제를 구체적으로 정의하는
type of scenarios is very different from the computer
것은 컴퓨터 비전과 매우
visions.
다릅니다.
I would like to say computer vision is mostly
저는 컴퓨터 비전이 주로 입력, 즉
about trying to learn some kind of representations
고차원 데이터를 기반으로 환경의
of the environment based on the inputs,
어떤 표현을 학습하려고 하는 것이라고
like high-dimensional data.
말하고 싶습니다.
But for robotics, it's basically trying
하지만 로봇 공학은
to solve some kind of optimization problems
기본적으로 물리적 환경의 제약을
where you have the constraints, which
가진 최적화 문제를
is a physical world of the environment.
해결하려고 합니다.
You have your objective functions
목표에 대해 정의된
defined over your goal.
목표 함수가 있습니다.
And you are essentially trying to solve this optimization
그리고 본질적으로 목표 함수를
problems by coming up with a sequence of actions
최대화하거나 최소화할 수 있는 일련의 행동을
that can maximize or minimize your objective functions.
제시함으로써 이 최적화 문제를 해결하려고 합니다.
So that's a key difference between robot learning
그래서 로봇 학습과 사람들이 일반적으로
and what people typically consider in computer vision.
컴퓨터 비전에서 고려하는 것 사이의 주요 차이점입니다.
So some specific instantiations of this problem
이 문제의 특정 인스턴스 예를
like, for example, cart-pole, the goal
들면, 카트-폴에서 목표는 이동 가능한
can be balance a pole on the top of a movable cart.
카트 위에 막대를 균형 있게 유지하는 것입니다.
And the states of this environment
이 환경의 상태는
essentially describe the physical state status
시스템의 물리적 상태를
of the systems, which can include the angle, the angular
설명하며, 각도, 각속도, 위치,
speed, positions, horizontal velocities, et cetera.
수평 속도 등을 포함할 수 있습니다.
And the action would be the horizontal force
행동은 카트에 적용되는
that is applied to the carts.
수평 힘이 될 것입니다.
And you can have the rewards where 1 indicating at each time
그리고 보상은 각 시간 단계에서 막대가
step if the poll is being kept as an upright position.
수직 위치를 유지하고 있는지를 나타내는 1이 될 수 있습니다.
Some other example could include robot locomotion,
다른 예로는 로봇 보행이 포함될 수 있으며, 목표는
where the goal is to make these robots move forwards.
이 로봇들이 앞으로 이동하도록 하는 것입니다.
And the states could include the angle position velocities
상태는 이 로봇의 모든 관절의 각도 위치
of all joints within this robot.
속도를 포함할 수 있습니다.
And the action could be the torque applied
행동은 각 관절에
to each one of the joints.
적용되는 토크일 수 있습니다.
And the reward can be 1 at each time.
보상은 매 시간마다 1일 수 있습니다.
The robot make a step forwards and also being
로봇은 앞으로 한 걸음을 내딛고 똑바로
kept in an upright positions.
서 있는 상태를 유지합니다.
And also some interesting examples
그리고 아타리 게임을 포함한 흥미로운
including the Atari games.
예시도 있습니다.
The goal can be complete the game with the highest score, as
목표는 가능한 한 높은 점수로 게임을
high as possible you can get.
완료하는 것입니다.
And the states will be the raw pixel inputs
상태는 게임 화면의 원시 픽셀
of the gaming screen.
입력이 될 것입니다.
And action could be the gaming control like up, down, left,
행동은 위, 아래, 왼쪽, 오른쪽과 같은 게임 조작일 수
and right.
있습니다.
And the reward could be the score increase
보상은 매 시간 단계에서
and decrease at each time step.
점수의 증가와 감소일 수 있습니다.
And some of the more famous examples you
그리고 여러분이 아마도 이전에 주목했을 유명한
probably have noticed earlier, especially
예시들이 있으며, 특히 AlphaGo의
with the developments of AlphaGo.
발전과 관련이 있습니다.
And the definition and the problem of Go
바둑의 정의와 문제는 게임에서
can also be defined in similar ways, where
이기는 것이 목표인 유사한
the goal is to win the game.
방식으로 정의될 수 있습니다.
And the states will be all the pieces that are currently
상태는 현재 바둑판에 있는 모든
already on the Go board.
돌이 될 것입니다.
And action could be where to put the next piece down
행동은 이 보드에 다음 돌을 놓을 위치가
on this board.
될 수 있습니다.
And the reward could be, on the last turn, if you win,
보상은 마지막 턴에서 이기면
you get a reward of 1, and if you lose, you get a reward of 0.
1의 보상을 받고, 지면 0의 보상을 받는 것입니다.
And this not only applies to, for example, gaming domains.
이것은 예를 들어 게임 도메인에만 적용되는 것이 아닙니다.
Even with the recent developments of large language
최근의 대형 언어 모델 발전과 함께,
models, you can also think about those problems,
특히 순차 생성 문제에 대해
especially for sequential generation problems,
유사한 방식으로 생각할 수 있으며, 목표는
in a similar manner where the goal could
다음 단어를 예측하는
be to predict the next word.
것이 될 수 있습니다.
And the states could be the current words in the sentence.
상태는 문장에서 현재 단어들일 수 있습니다.
And the action will be what the specific next words
행동은 여러분이 그곳에 넣고 싶은 특정
you want to put there.
다음 단어가 될 것입니다.
And if it is correct, you get the reward.
정확하다면 보상을 받습니다.
If it is incorrect, you get a reward of 0.
부정확하다면 0의 보상을 받습니다.
And similarly, now, you probably have already
유사하게, 이제 여러분은
played with many of the chatbots quite a lot.
아마도 많은 챗봇과 많이 놀아보았을 것입니다.
And you can also define a problem similarly,
문제를 유사하게 정의할 수 있으며,
where the goal is to be a good companion to the human user.
목표는 인간 사용자에게 좋은 동반자가 되는 것입니다.
The states could be the current conversation.
상태는 현재 대화입니다.
And action that should be generated by the chatbots
챗봇이 생성해야 할 행동은 인간 사용자에게
will be the next sentence you are given to the human user.
주어지는 다음 문장이 될 것입니다.
And according to the human evaluations,
인간 평가에 따라, 사람이
we could define the reward if the person is happy.
행복하면 보상을 정의할 수 있습니다.
If they are satisfied, you get a reward of 1.
만족하면 1의 보상을 받습니다.
And if you are not happy or neutral,
행복하지 않거나 중립적이면
you get some other rewards.
다른 보상을 받습니다.
And more specifically, for example, in the robotics domain.
더 구체적으로, 예를 들어 로봇 공학 분야에서.
And the task could be to fold the clothes.
작업은 옷을 접는 것입니다.
And we want the clothes-- we fold it nicely.
우리는 옷을 잘 접고 싶습니다.
And the states is the current observations
상태는 로봇이 이 환경에서
the robot is getting from this environment, which
얻는 현재 관찰로, 다중 시점
could include the multi-view RGB or RGBD
RGB 또는 RGBD 관찰을
observations of the environment.
포함할 수 있습니다.
And the robot needs to decide its actions,
로봇은 자신의 행동, 즉 끝단 효과기를 어떻게
how to move its end-effectors.
움직일지를 결정해야 합니다.
Should it close or open its grippers
이 천을 조작하기 위해 그리퍼를 닫아야
in order to manipulate this cloth?
할까요, 아니면 열어야 할까요?
And according to human evaluations,
인간 평가에 따르면,
if the cloth is properly folded, it gives the robot
천이 제대로 접혀 있으면 로봇에게
a reward of 1, and if the cloth is not folded,
1의 보상을 주고, 접혀 있지 않으면
you give the reward of 0.
0의 보상을 줍니다.
So here is actually how you want to more concretely think
그래서 여기서 로봇 학습 문제를 더 구체적으로 생각하는
about robot learning problem.
방법을 설명하겠습니다.
It really is a way that allows the agents to interact
이는 에이전트가 세상과 상호작용할 수 있게 해주는
with the world.
방법입니다.
It considers the effect of an action
행동의 효과와 순차적
and also the sequential decision-making problems.
의사결정 문제를 고려합니다.
That is different from what people typically
이는 사람들이 일반적으로 컴퓨터 비전에서
consider in computer vision.
고려하는 것과 다릅니다.
We just need to predict the outputs.
우리는 단지 출력을 예측해야 합니다.
And the goal, states, actions, and the rewards
목표, 상태, 행동, 보상 및
and the objective functions are the things
목적 함수는 이 방향의
you need to keep in mind whenever
문제를 생각할
you are thinking about problems along this direction.
때 항상 염두에 두어야 할 사항입니다.
So this is about problem formulation.
이것은 문제 공식화에 관한 것입니다.
So question is how specific the reward needs to be designed.
질문은 보상이 얼마나 구체적으로 설계되어야 하는가입니다.
In many of the tasks, the reward can have many different types
많은 작업에서 보상은 다양한 유형의 사양을
of specifications.
가질 수 있습니다.
For example, in the self-driving,
예를 들어,
the reward could be as fast as possible or reward could
자율주행에서는 보상이 가능한 한 빨리 도착하는
be like we want the passengers to feel comfortable as you
것이거나, 승객이 도로를 주행하는 동안 편안함을 느끼도록 하는
are driving along the roads.
것일 수 있습니다.
So even for clothes folding, depending
옷 접기에서도 사용자의 선호에
on the user's preference, our clothes
따라 옷을 여러 가지
can be folded in many different ways.
방법으로 접을 수 있습니다.
Some want the total area to be as small as possible.
어떤 사람들은 전체 면적이 가능한 한 작기를 원합니다.
Some want it to be as smooth as possible.
어떤 사람들은 가능한 한 매끄럽기를 원합니다.
There could be different types of rewards.
다양한 유형의 보상이 있을 수 있습니다.
Here, I'm just talking in generic terms.
여기서는 일반적인 용어로 이야기하고 있습니다.
If a person looks at the clothes,
사람이 옷을 보면, 이것이
do they think, this is folded, or not?
접혀 있다고 생각할까요, 아니면 아닐까요?
But more specifically, in terms of the reward design,
하지만 보상 설계 측면에서 더
there's actually a lot of nuances
구체적으로 말하자면, 특정
satisfying a specific need of a specific application.
애플리케이션의 특정 요구를 충족하는 데 많은 뉘앙스가 있습니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
So I'll continue.
계속하겠습니다.
So this is how we are thinking about those robot learning
이것이 에이전트가 물리적 세계와
problem that allows the agents to interact
상호작용할 수 있게 해주는 로봇 학습
with the physical world.
문제를 생각하는 방법입니다.
Now, I'm moving on to robot perception,
이제 로봇 인식으로 넘어가겠습니다.
especially in discussing how the perception
특히 로봇 학습 영역 내에서 인식
problem within this robot learning domain
문제가 사람들이 일반적으로
is different from what people typically
컴퓨터 비전에서 고려하는 것과
consider in computer vision.
어떻게 다른지 논의하겠습니다.
So this image again--
이 이미지는
you're actually going to see this image again and again
오늘 강의에서 여러 번
through today's lecture.
보게 될 것입니다.
So this is, essentially, in the question
본질적으로, 이것은 우리가
of how we are handling whatever information you are getting
물리적 세계에서 얻는 정보를 어떻게 처리하는가에
from the physical world.
대한 질문입니다.
The physical world can give you, for example,
물리적 세계는 예를 들어,
high-dimensional RGB observation or RGBD observations.
고차원 RGB 관찰 또는 RGBD 관찰을 제공할 수 있습니다.
It could also include some other sensory data
또한 촉각 감지와 같은 다른 감각
like tactile sensings.
데이터를 포함할 수 있습니다.
And this robot perception problem
이 로봇 인식 문제는
is essentially trying to distill or harness
본질적으로 이러한 고차원 데이터에서
some structured knowledge from those high-dimensional data that
로봇이 하위 의사결정을 하는 데 유용한
is useful for the robot to do the downstream decision making.
구조화된 지식을 증류하거나 활용하려고 합니다.
And essentially, the question we are trying to tackle
본질적으로 우리가 해결하려고 하는 질문은 이
is trying to make sense of this unstructured real world.
비구조적 현실 세계를 이해하려고 하는 것입니다.
And the real world can be very messy.
현실 세계는 매우 복잡할 수 있습니다.
So essentially, the observations the robots
따라서 로봇이 환경에서
are getting from the environments
얻는 관찰은 객체와
can only contain incomplete knowledge of the objects
환경에 대한 불완전한 지식만 포함할
and the environments.
수 있습니다.
There could be occlusions.
차단이 있을 수 있습니다.
There could also be errors from the sensory data.
감각 데이터에서 오류가 발생할 수 있습니다.
And the imperfect action may also lead to failure.
불완전한 행동도 실패로 이어질 수 있습니다.
For example, the robots can try to grasp some objects,
예를 들어, 로봇은 물체를 잡으려고 시도할 수 있지만, 그들의
but their grasping behavior may not always be successful.
잡기 행동이 항상 성공적이지는 않을 수 있습니다.
Sometimes, you will accidentally drop that object,
때때로, 물체를 실수로 떨어뜨릴 수
which will also cause evolutions and unexpected changes
있으며, 이는 환경의 진화와 예상치 못한 변화를 초래할
of this environment.
수 있습니다.
They will also need to have this perception system that is
그들은 이러한 시나리오를 처리할 수 있는
able to handle those scenarios.
인식 시스템을 가져야 합니다.
And also this environment can change.
또한 이 환경은 변할 수 있습니다.
It is dynamic, consists of not just rigid object
이 환경은 동적이며, 단단한 물체뿐만 아니라
but deformable object-- clothes, ropes, granular medias.
변형 가능한 물체(옷, 로프, 입자 매체)로 구성됩니다.
There could be other agents, like dogs or other kids
개나 다른 아이들, 다른 인간과 같은 다른
or other humans that are also in the same environments,
에이전트가 같은 환경에 존재하여 세상을
messing up with the world.
어지럽힐 수 있습니다.
And your perception system needs to be
따라서 당신의 인식 시스템은 이러한
able to cope with all those kind of changes.
모든 종류의 변화에 대처할 수 있어야 합니다.
So that is why, in the robotics domain,
그래서 로봇 공학 분야에서는 사람들이
people typically not just work with a camera data.
일반적으로 카메라 데이터만 가지고 작업하지 않습니다.
They try to add as much sensor as possible to the robots
그들은 가능한 한 많은 센서를 로봇에 추가하려고 하며,
as long as they can provide some useful informations.
유용한 정보를 제공할 수 있는 한도 내에서 그렇게 합니다.
It's really considered, for example, the tactile sensings,
예를 들어, 촉각 감지, 오디오
the audio information, the depth information, et cetera.
정보, 깊이 정보 등을 고려합니다.
And typically, we will have to design a system that
일반적으로 우리는 모든 센서를 함께 결합하여
is able to put all the sensors together
서로 보완할 수 있는 시스템을
that allows them to complement each other,
설계해야 하며, 모든 정보는 물리적
whereas all the information might tell you things
맥락에 대한 정보를
about the physical context.
제공할 수 있습니다.
And the tactile information might tell you
촉각 정보는 그래프가 안정적인지
about whether a graph is stable or not.
여부를 알려줄 수 있습니다.
And the camera information tells you
카메라 정보는 이
about something that is more on the higher level,
환경의 전반적인 상태에
on the grand scheme of things, about the overall state
대한 더 높은 수준의 정보를
of this environment.
제공합니다.
So how these sensors can be composed together
이러한 센서들이 어떻게 결합되어
and work together is very, very important
함께 작동할 수 있는지가 실제
to design a capable robotic system that are working
물리적 세계에서 작동하는 유능한 로봇
in the real physical world.
시스템을 설계하는 데 매우 중요합니다.
And besides the numbers of sensory modalities,
감각 양식의 수 외에도 로봇 비전과 컴퓨터
very important difference between a robot vision
비전의 중요한
and computer vision is trying to really understand
차이점은 행동의 효과와 이 환경의
the effect of the actions and also the affordance
가능성을 이해하려고
of this environment.
한다는 것입니다.
On the left is a very typical example
왼쪽은 컴퓨터 비전에서 이미
you have already seen in computer vision, which is trying
본 전형적인 예로, 인스턴스 분할을
to do instance segmentation.
시도하는 것입니다.
What you are given is this 2D image.
주어진 것은 이 2D 이미지입니다.
You have segments, different instances from this 2D image,
이 2D 이미지에서 서로 다른 인스턴스를
like by drawing a contour over this 2D pixels.
세그먼트로 나누며, 2D 픽셀 위에 윤곽선을 그립니다.
But what's different in the robotics domain, for example,
하지만 로봇 공학 분야에서의 차이점은
on the right--
오른쪽과 같이 로봇이
the robot can, for example, given one object.
하나의 물체를 주어진 경우입니다.
And this object seems to be maybe just one object or maybe
이 물체는 아마도 하나의 물체일 수도 있고, 서로
a lot of pieces that are, for example, stacked
쌓여 있는 여러 조각일
into each other.
수도 있습니다.
So the robot has to know what type of actions
따라서 로봇은 어떤 종류의 행동이 이 환경에
will allow it to have better understanding, better
대한 더 나은 이해와 인식을 가능하게
perceptions about this environment.
할지를 알아야 합니다.
Is this one piece of object or multiple
이것이 하나의 물체인지 아니면 여러
pieces composed together?
조각이 결합된 것인지?
So the robot should come up with actions like perturb
그래서 로봇은 환경과 능동적으로
and actively interact with the environments for the robot
상호작용하고 방해하는 행동을 통해 이
to get a better perception about the state of this environment.
환경의 상태에 대한 더 나은 인식을 얻어야 합니다.
So that is why a robot vision is embodied, active, and also
그래서 로봇 비전은 구현되고, 능동적이며,
environmentally situated.
환경에 적합합니다.
By embodied, what we mean is robots
구현된다는 것은 로봇이
have this kind of physical body that is directly experiencing
물리적 세계를 직접 경험하는 신체를 가지고
the physical world directly.
있다는 의미입니다.
Their actions are part of a dynamic
그들의 행동은 즉각적인
with the world that have immediate feedback
피드백을 받는 세계와의
on their own sensations.
동적 관계의 일부입니다.
And active, meaning the robots are active perceivers.
능동적이라는 것은 로봇이 능동적인 인식자라는 의미입니다.
It knows why it wishes to sense and chooses what to perceive
로봇은 무엇을 감지하고 싶은지 알고, 무엇을 인식할지를
and determines how and when and where
선택하며, 그 인식을 달성하기 위해 어떻게,
to achieve that perception.
언제, 어디서 할지를 결정합니다.
You can move your head around.
당신은 머리를 움직일 수 있습니다.
If you want to know what's behind this table,
이 테이블 뒤에 무엇이 있는지 알고 싶다면,
you can just move around to see what's behind the table.
주위를 돌아다니며 테이블 뒤를 볼 수 있습니다.
So this is the active part, which
그래서 이것이 활성 부분이며, 이는
is different from what people typically
사람들이 일반적으로 컴퓨터
consider in computer vision.
비전에서 고려하는 것과 다릅니다.
They are mostly working with a passively collected data set.
그들은 주로 수동적으로 수집된 데이터 세트로 작업하고 있습니다.
The third point is about situated,
세 번째 포인트는 로봇이 세계에
where the robots are situated in the world.
위치하는 것에 관한 것입니다.
They do not deal with abstract descriptions but with the here
그들은 추상적인 설명이 아니라 시스템의
and now of the world directly influencing
행동에 직접 영향을 미치는
the behavior of the systems.
현재의 세계와 다루고 있습니다.
Robots really have to understand, especially
로봇은 특히 의류에서 인식과
in clothing, there's perception and action loop.
행동 루프를 이해해야 합니다.
It sees the world and understand its goals
로봇은 세상을 보고 목표를 이해하며
and be able to act in the environment
인식에 따라 환경에서 행동할
upon its perceptions.
수 있어야 합니다.
Sometimes, the robot don't have to know the full state
때때로 로봇은 환경의 전체 상태를 알
of the environment.
필요가 없습니다.
For example, if I'm buttoning my shirt,
예를 들어, 내가 셔츠의
I only have to know the local regions near that button for me
단추를 채우고 있다면, 그 단추 근처의 지역만
to button that shirt.
알면 됩니다.
So some of the perception has to be
그래서 일부 인식은
tightly coupled and co-designed with the task
작업 및 하위 의사 결정
and the downstream decision-making
시스템과 밀접하게
systems for the robot to focus on the relevant region
결합되고 공동 설계되어
or task-relevant regions of the environment to be properly--
로봇이 관련 지역 또는 작업 관련
a closest perception and action loop.
지역에 집중할 수 있도록 해야 합니다.
So this is about some very specific considerations
그래서 이것은 매우 구체적인 고려 사항과 로봇의 인식이
and how robots' perception might be
사람들이 일반적으로 컴퓨터
different from what people typically
비전에서 고려하는 것과 어떻게
consider in computer vision.
다를 수 있는지에 관한 것입니다.
I will be starting to discuss some of the algorithms that
로봇이 세상을 보고 행동할 수
not only allow the robot to see but allow
있게 해주는 알고리즘에 대해
the robot to act in the world.
논의하기 시작할 것입니다.
And we'll start with reinforcement learning.
그리고 우리는 강화 학습으로 시작할 것입니다.
Remember, earlier, we have seen this image.
기억하세요, 이전에 우리는 이 이미지를 보았습니다.
The robot has to act upon this environment
로봇은 이 환경에서 행동하고 이
and get rewards from this environment.
환경으로부터 보상을 받아야 합니다.
So one very typical way of trying
이 최적화 문제를 해결하기
to solve this optimization problem
위한 매우 일반적인 방법은
is allow the robots to interact with the world as extensively
로봇이 가능한 한 광범위하게 세계와
and as massively as possible.
상호작용하도록 하는 것입니다.
You just collect all the experience data
모든 경험 데이터를 수집하고
and do this type of trials and errors.
이러한 유형의 시행착오를 수행합니다.
Allow the robots to understand this action leads to high reward
로봇이 이 행동이 높은 보상으로 이어지고 저 행동이 낮은
and that action leads to lower rewards.
보상으로 이어진다는 것을 이해하도록 합니다.
And we can pivot the agents' behaviors
그리고 우리는 에이전트의 행동을 에이전트에게
towards the actions that give the agent some higher rewards.
더 높은 보상을 주는 행동으로 전환할 수 있습니다.
So this is the general ideas of reinforcement learning
그래서 강화 학습의 일반적인 아이디어는
is really a way to allow the agents to constantly interact
에이전트가 환경과 지속적으로 상호작용하고 보상을
with the environment and do this trial
극대화하거나 비용을 최소화하기
and error to maximize the reward or minimize the cost.
위해 시행착오를 수행할 수 있도록 하는 방법입니다.
And here I also want to be a bit more specific in discussing
여기서 저는 강화 학습과 감독 학습의
the difference between reinforcement learning
차이에 대해 좀 더 구체적으로
and supervised learning.
논의하고 싶습니다.
So this is a typical framework of how reinforcement learning
그래서 이것이 강화 학습의 전형적인
looks like.
프레임워크입니다.
You have the environments.
당신은 환경을 가지고 있습니다.
Environment gives the agent some states.
환경은 에이전트에게 몇 가지 상태를 제공합니다.
Agents generate actions.
에이전트는 행동을 생성합니다.
And environments give the agent a feedback, which is the reward.
그리고 환경은 에이전트에게 피드백, 즉 보상을 제공합니다.
And environments will change, where the environment will
환경은 변화하며, 환경은
give the agents the new states, st plus 1,
에이전트에게 새로운 상태 st+1을
and essentially a sequence, like a temporal sequence
제공하고 본질적으로 로봇이
on the temporal domain where the robot has to-- the agent
연속적인 결정을 내려야 하는
has to make this sequential decisions.
시간 도메인에서의 시퀀스와 같습니다.
And here is a typical image typically
여기 감독 학습을 위한 전형적인
look like for supervised learning.
이미지가 있습니다.
So you have the data set.
당신은 데이터 세트를 가지고 있습니다.
The data set will input to the model this x.
데이터 세트는 모델에 이 x를 입력합니다.
And this model will generate the prediction y.
그리고 이 모델은 예측 y를 생성합니다.
And you will be able to calculate the loss according
그리고 당신은 모델의 예측과 이
to the model's predictions versus the ground
데이터 세트의 실제 값에 따라 손실을
truth from this data sets.
계산할 수 있습니다.
So this is a typical setup of supervised learning.
그래서 이것이 감독 학습의 전형적인 설정입니다.
And the key difference-- some of the key differences
강화 학습과 지도 학습의
between reinforcement learning and supervised learning
주요 차이점 중 하나는
is that the environments might be stochastic
환경이 확률적일 수 있으며, 동일한 행동이
or the same actions, the environment
환경을 다르게 변화시킬
might change in a different manner.
수 있다는 점입니다.
Let's say, if you are pushing a box forward,
예를 들어, 상자를 앞으로
depending on the distribution of the supporting force,
밀 때, 지지력의 분포에
the same exact actions will lead to-- can potentially
따라 동일한 행동이 상자가 다른 각도로
lead to the box rotating into different angles,
회전하게 만들 수 있으며,
meaning there can be uncertainties and stochasticity
이는 환경에서 불확실성과
in the environments that will lead
확률성이 존재할 수 있음을 의미합니다.
to a stochastic behavior of these environments, which
이는 에이전트에게도 확률적
will also give these agents stochastic rewards, where
보상을 주며, 동일한 행동이 항상 동일한
the same action may not always lead to the same rewards.
보상으로 이어지지 않을 수 있습니다.
So this is very different from supervised learning.
그래서 이는 지도 학습과 매우 다릅니다.
We are dealing with an uncertain dynamical system.
우리는 불확실한 동적 시스템을 다루고 있습니다.
The second is about the question of credit assignments.
두 번째는 신용 할당에 관한 질문입니다.
So for supervised learning, you give the inputs,
지도 학습에서는 입력을 제공하고
you predict the outputs, and you already calculate the loss.
출력을 예측하며 손실을 이미 계산합니다.
Now, you directly know what are the mistakes
이제 특정 예측을 통해 어떤 실수를 하고
and what are the errors you are making by making
있는지, 어떤 오류를 범하고 있는지
a specific prediction.
직접 알 수 있습니다.
But in the reinforcement learning
하지만 강화
or sequential decision-making domain,
학습이나 순차적 의사결정
the rewards can be delayed, meaning
영역에서는 보상이 지연될 수
if you play the game of Go, only until the very end
있습니다. 즉, 바둑 게임을 할 때, 이 에피소드의
of this episode, do you realize you are winning
끝까지 가야만 이기고 있는지 지고
or you were losing.
있는지를 알 수 있습니다.
And that rewards there 01.
그리고 그 보상은 01입니다.
[INAUDIBLE] is because of some very, very early steps, maybe
[듣기 어려움] 이는 매우 초기 단계, 아마도
even the first steps or some steps
첫 단계나 게임 중간의 몇
during the middle of the games.
단계 때문입니다.
So how do you properly assign the credits
따라서 이 순차적 의사결정
you are getting along this sequential decision making
과정에서 얻는 신용을 모든 행동에
towards all the actions is also another very tricky
적절히 할당하는 방법도 사람들이 강화 학습을
and important question people hope to answer
통해 답하고자 하는 또 다른 매우
using reinforcement learning.
까다롭고 중요한 질문입니다.
The third thing is the nondiffusion abilities
세 번째는 이 동적 시스템의 비확산
of this dynamical systems.
능력입니다.
For example, for supervised learning, you have the inputs.
예를 들어, 지도 학습에서는 입력이 있습니다.
You feed the inputs through the model.
모델을 통해 입력을 전달합니다.
You get the outputs.
출력을 얻습니다.
You calculate the loss.
손실을 계산합니다.
So everything along this process is differentiable.
따라서 이 과정의 모든 것은 미분 가능하다.
So you can directly gather gradients of the loss functions
그래서 모델 내의 매개변수에 대한 손실 함수의
with respect to the parameters within the model.
기울기를 직접 수집할 수 있다.
But that's typically not the case
하지만 강화
for reinforcement learning where the environments can oftentimes
학습에서는 환경이 종종 미분 가능하지 않은
not differentiable.
경우가 많다.
So how do you properly get the gradients
따라서 행동에 대한 보상의
of the rewards with respect to the actions can be tricky.
기울기를 제대로 얻는 것은 까다로울 수 있다.
Sometimes, people have to realize on a massive sampling
때때로 사람들은 적절한 학습을 위해
to do those type of zero order estimations of the gradients
이러한 제로 차수 기울기 추정을 수행하기 위해 대규모
for you to do proper learning.
샘플링에 의존해야 한다.
That also is another difference.
그것도 또 다른 차이점이다.
The last difference is about this nonstationarity
마지막 차이점은 환경의 진화와
of this scenarios where the evolutions
상태가 당신의 행동의 결과라는
and the states of the environments
비정상성에
is really a result of your actions.
관한 것이다.
For supervised learning, whatever you predict,
지도 학습에서는 예측한 것이 이 데이터
it doesn't influence other data points you
세트에서 얻는 다른 데이터
are getting from this data set.
포인트에 영향을 미치지 않는다.
But your actions will influence the next state
하지만 당신의 행동은 이 순차적
you are getting in this sequential decision-making
의사결정 문제에서 얻는 다음 상태에 영향을
problems.
미친다.
That is also what makes this kind of reinforcement learning
그것이 바로 이 강화 학습
problem a little bit more nuanced
문제를 지도 학습보다 조금
than supervised learning.
더 미묘하게 만드는 이유이다.
So here are some more specific examples.
여기 몇 가지 더 구체적인 예가 있다.
Like for example, playing this Atari games,
예를 들어, 앞서 언급한 것처럼 이 아타리
like I mentioned earlier.
게임을 하는 것이다.
The goal could be to complete the games with the highest
목표는 가장 높은 점수로 게임을 완료하는
score.
것이다.
And the states would be the raw pixel inputs
상태는 게임 화면의 원시 픽셀
from the gaming screen.
입력이 될 것이다.
And the action could be up, down, left,
행동은 키보드에서 위, 아래,
and right from the keyboard.
왼쪽, 오른쪽이 될 수 있다.
And we're trying to--
우리는 각
the rewards are the score increase and decrease
시간 단계에서 점수의 증가와 감소가
at each time step.
보상인 것을 시도하고 있다.
And some typical algorithms within this domain
이 분야의 전형적인 알고리즘은
either lies in the field of, for example,
예를 들어 Q-학습이나
like a Q-learning or, for example, policy iterations.
정책 반복과 같은 분야에 있습니다.
Here's my examples of trying to learn this Q function.
여기 Q 함수를 학습하려는 제 예시가 있습니다.
Q function essentially measures the discounted expected future
Q 함수는 본질적으로 특정 상태 s에서 특정 행동 a를
accumulated rewards like when you apply a specific action a at
적용할 때 할인된 기대 미래 누적
a specific state s.
보상을 측정합니다.
And you will be able to get these Q
이 게임 환경과의
functions through interactions with this gaming environments.
상호작용을 통해 이러한 Q 함수를 얻을 수 있습니다.
And after you have learned this Q functions,
이 Q 함수를 학습한 후에는
you can evaluate, for example, what
다양한 행동을 적용하여
are the Q values you are getting by applying different actions.
얻는 Q 값을 평가할 수 있습니다.
In this case, there's left and right, ups and downs.
이 경우 왼쪽과 오른쪽, 위와 아래가 있습니다.
So there could potentially be four actions.
따라서 잠재적으로 네 가지 행동이 있을 수 있습니다.
And given these four actions, you can look at their Q values
이 네 가지 행동을 고려하여 Q 값을 보고
and just execute the actions that
가장 높은 Q 값을 주는 행동을
give you the highest Q values.
실행할 수 있습니다.
So that is what allows you to do this type of decision
이것이 이 분야에서 이러한 유형의
making in this domain.
의사 결정을 가능하게 합니다.
Because today we're going to cover a lot of materials,
오늘 많은 자료를 다룰 것이기 때문에
so we won't go into the details of the reinforcement learning.
강화 학습의 세부 사항에 들어가지 않을 것입니다.
But some of the current state-of-the-art reinforcement
하지만 SAC, 소프트 액터 비평가
learning algorithms, including SAC, Soft Actor Critic,
및 PPO, 근접 정책 최적화와 같은 현재의
and also PPO, Proximal Policy Optimization.
최첨단 강화 학습 알고리즘이 있습니다.
So if you are interested, you are
관심이 있으시면 이러한
very welcome to look at those algorithms in detail.
알고리즘을 자세히 살펴보시기 바랍니다.
There's a lot of open source implementations and tutorials
온라인에는 많은 오픈 소스 구현 및 튜토리얼이
online.
있습니다.
But here I want to highlight to you
하지만 여기서는
some of the results you could potentially
강화 학습, 특히 Q-학습
get by going through this reinforcement learning,
과정을 통해 얻을 수 있는 결과
specifically Q-learning process.
몇 가지를 강조하고 싶습니다.
This is developed by Google DeepMind that
이것은 Google DeepMind에서
is trying to develop these agents, that
개발한 것으로, Atari
is trying to play the game Breakout in this kind of Atari
세계에서 Breakout 게임을 하려고 하는 에이전트를 개발하고
world.
있습니다.
So just after 10 minutes of training, the robot,
훈련 10분 후, 로봇 에이전트는
the agent can already touch the ball
이미 공을 터치할 수 있지만,
but, oftentimes, can still miss the ball quite often.
종종 공을 놓치는 경우가 많습니다.
And after some more times of learning, for example,
그리고 더 많은 학습 후,
two hours of training, and the agents
예를 들어 2시간의 훈련을 통해
can control this kind of paths in a much more
에이전트는 훨씬 더 신뢰할 수
reliable and consistent fashion that can, nearly all the time,
있고 일관된 방식으로 경로를 제어할
can catch the ball and be able to constantly get
수 있으며, 거의 항상
more and more rewards by bouncing back.
공을 잡고 지속적으로 더 많은 보상을 받을 수 있습니다.
And after full hours of training, something that's
훈련이 4시간이 지나면 흥미로운 일이
interesting happens, where the agents come up with, actually,
발생하는데, 에이전트가 사실상 많은
a novel strategy, which possibly is not known to many of you,
사람들에게 알려지지 않은 새로운 전략을
that is, trying to push, bounce the ball
고안하게 됩니다. 즉, 공을
back to create the tunnel on the left side of this wall.
밀어 벽의 왼쪽에 터널을 만드는 것입니다.
And then it will push this ball on the upper side of the wall
그리고 벽의 윗부분에서 이 공을
to do this very efficient reductions of those bricks.
밀어 이 벽돌들을 매우 효율적으로 제거합니다.
This is the type of strategy that
이것은 강화 학습을
can be discovered by reinforcement learning.
통해 발견할 수 있는 전략의 유형입니다.
So this is what's nice about reinforcement
그래서 강화 학습의 장점은
learning, meaning you allow the agents to do very extensive
에이전트가 세계와 매우 광범위하고 포괄적인 탐색 및
and comprehensive exploration and interactions with the world.
상호작용을 할 수 있게 한다는 것입니다.
And it is totally possible for this reinforcement learning
이 강화 학습 에이전트가 최고의 인간
agents to discover some strategies that
플레이어보다 더 나은 전략을
are better than even the best human players.
발견하는 것이 전혀 불가능하지 않습니다.
A very typical example would be the game of Go.
매우 전형적인 예는 바둑 게임입니다.
So when AlphaGo came out in the January 2016,
2016년 1월에 AlphaGo가
it was also about the time when I
등장했을 때, 제가 어떤 연구
was trying to decide what type of research directions
방향을 정할지 고민하던
I'm going to go.
시기였습니다.
Before that time, I was just working on deep
그 이전에는 컴퓨터 비전을 위한 딥러닝
learning for computer vision.
작업만 하고 있었습니다.
But when AlphaGo came out, I'm like,
하지만 AlphaGo가 나왔을 때, 저는 이러한 의사
I have to work on this kind of decision-making problem.
결정 문제에 대해 작업해야겠다고 생각했습니다.
So that's why I started to touch upon reinforcement learning,
그래서 강화 학습, 모방 학습에 대해 다루기
imitation learning, and, all the way until now,
시작했고, 지금까지 로봇 학습을
to do robot learning that allows the robots to do
통해 로봇이 환경과 물리적 상호작용을
physical interactions with the environments.
할 수 있도록 하고 있습니다.
So I wasn't satisfied with just working
저는 단순히 수집된 데이터 세트로
with a passively collected data set,
작업하는 것에 만족하지 않았고,
but we really want an agent that can do active interactions
환경과 능동적으로 상호작용할 수 있는
with the environment.
에이전트를 원했습니다.
So the question was, how does specifically
그래서 질문은 이 Q 함수가 구체적으로
this Q-function works?
어떻게 작동하는가였습니다.
So you can see, this Q takes as input
보시다시피, 이 Q는 상태 s와
the state s and also the action.
행동을 입력으로 받습니다.
And this data would essentially be the parameters
이 데이터는 본질적으로 Q
of this Q function, where the Q is instantiated
함수의 매개변수가 되며, Q는
as a neural network.
신경망으로 인스턴스화됩니다.
In this specific case, like I mentioned earlier,
이 특정 경우, 제가 앞서
the state is the raw pixel inputs
언급한 것처럼 상태는 실제로 게임
that you're actually getting from the gaming screen.
화면에서 얻는 원시 픽셀 입력입니다.
So the inputs could be this four steps,
따라서 입력은 이 네 단계, 네
four frames that are directly inputted to this Q function.
프레임이 이 Q 함수에 직접 입력될 수 있습니다.
And if you are dealing with images,
이미지를 다룰 때, 이
a very straightforward way of instantiating this Q function
Q 함수를 구현하는 매우 직관적인 방법은 합성곱
is to use convolutional neural networks.
신경망을 사용하는 것입니다.
So you have convolutional layers like shown
이런 종류의 주황색 블록처럼
in this kind of orange blocks.
합성곱 층이 있습니다.
And then you'll be able to go through this fully connected
그런 다음 완전 연결 층을
layers to directly derive this Q value.
통해 이 Q 값을 직접 도출할 수 있습니다.
And in this case, because there are four discrete actions--
이 경우, 네 개의 이산 행동이 있기 때문에-- 아마도
in this case, probably just left and right.
왼쪽과 오른쪽입니다.
But let's say there's four discrete actions-- up and down,
하지만 네 개의 이산 행동이 있다고 가정해 봅시다-- 위와 아래,
left and right.
왼쪽과 오른쪽.
So you will be able to have different Q value
따라서 특정 행동 a의 결과로
estimations that is the results of this specific action a.
서로 다른 Q 값 추정치를 가질 수 있습니다.
And that's how you can use these Q values to make decisions
이렇게 Q 값을 사용하여 가장
on what action to take that is the most effective
효과적이고 Q 값을 극대화하는 행동을
and maximizing this Q value.
결정할 수 있습니다.
Does that answer your question?
이 질문에 대한 답이 되었나요?
Yes, this is when AlphaGo came out.
네, 이것이 AlphaGo가 등장했을 때입니다.
And obviously, since then, there has
그리고 그 이후로 이러한
been a lot of developments and evolutions
유형의 게임 에이전트를 더
in making this type of gaming agents better and better.
나아지게 하는 많은 발전과 진화가 있었습니다.
So then later, there's AlphaGo Zero.
그 후 AlphaGo Zero가 나왔습니다.
That is essentially a simplified version of AlphaGo,
본질적으로 AlphaGo의 단순화된
then no longer using any imitation learning
버전으로, 더 이상
to do any initialization.
모방 학습을 사용하지 않습니다.
And it's able to beat, at that time, the number one
그 당시 1위 선수인 커제에게
player, Ke Jie.
이길 수 있었습니다.
So this is actually one thing, one lesson people learned
이것은 AI 커뮤니티에서 사람들이
inside this AI communities, which
배운 한 가지 교훈으로, 리치 서튼의
you can call it the bitter lesson from the Rich Sutton,
쓴 교훈이라고 부를 수
where sometimes you want to find the simplest recipes that
있습니다. 때때로 가장 간단한 레시피를
is the most and best compatible with the scaling.
찾는 것이 가장 잘 확장성과 호환됩니다.
You want to leverage the scale, the power of scalings.
확장의 힘을 활용하고 싶습니다.
And sometimes, making this method simpler
때때로 이 방법을
will actually give you better performance
단순화하면 더
by making it more compatible with whatever infrastructure
나은 성능을 제공할
you can use for scaling things up.
수 있습니다.
And then later, they develop Alpha Zero
그 후 Alpha Zero를 개발하여
that is able to generalize the same set of algorithms
동일한 알고리즘 세트를 체스와 쇼기와
into not just chess--
같은 다른
not just Go but other games like chess and shogi.
게임으로 일반화할 수 있게 되었습니다.
And then they designed MuZero that
그런 다음 모델 없는 강화 학습을 수행할
not just do this kind of model-free reinforcement
뿐만 아니라, 더 나은 성능을
learning, but it's able to learn a latent space dynamics
제공하는 잠재 공간 동역학
model to plan over that gives you an even better performance.
모델을 학습할 수 있는 MuZero를 설계했습니다.
So for this specific domain, I would say, especially
이 특정 도메인에서는 특히
in the gaming developments, that really empowers a lot of design
게임 개발에서 사람들이 더 나은 설계와 효율적인
and developments in how people can do better and more assembly
조립 및 확장 가능한 강화 학습 에이전트를
efficient and more scalable design of those reinforcement
설계하는 데 많은 힘을 주었다고
learning agents.
말할 수 있습니다.
And in November 2019, Lee Sedol, who was beaten by of AlphaGo,
2019년 11월, AlphaGo에게 패배한 이세돌이
announce his retirement.
은퇴를 발표했습니다.
And he realized they're just not--
그는 당시 어떤
it's just not possible, at that time, for any human players
인간 플레이어도 최고의 AI 에이전트를
to beat the best like AI agents out there.
이길 수 없다는 것을 깨달았습니다.
And obviously, since then, there has
그 이후로 스타크래프트와
been other more complex games like StarCraft and Dota
도타와 같은 더 복잡한
that shows that as long as you put enough compute, as long
게임이 등장했으며, 충분한 컴퓨팅
as you have a very well designed algorithms and infrastructure
자원과 잘 설계된 알고리즘 및 인프라가
for you to do the reinforcement learning,
있다면,
you can get very, very good performance in games that
실제로 바둑보다 훨씬 더 복잡한
are actually noticeably and orders of magnitude
게임에서도 매우
more complicated than the game of Go.
좋은 성능을 얻을 수 있습니다.
So I would say, if you have a game, a reasonably designed
따라서 합리적으로 설계된 게임이 있다면,
game, there's a very good chance,
충분한 자원을 투입하면 매우
if you put the sufficient resource,
강력한 게임 에이전트를 가질
you can have very, very powerful gaming agents.
수 있는 좋은 기회가 있습니다.
So not just in games, people have also
게임뿐만 아니라, 사람들은 실제
been developing this reinforcement learning
물리적 세계에서 직접
algorithms and agents that can work directly
작동할 수 있는 강화 학습 알고리즘과
in the real physical world.
에이전트도 개발하고 있습니다.
So this, on the left, is a work from ETH
왼쪽은 2020년 Science Robotics에
that was published in Science Robotics 2020.
발표된 ETH의 작업입니다.
That essentially changed my mind about how useful reinforcement
이는 강화 학습이 실제 물리적 로봇에 얼마나 유용할
learning can be for real physical robots
수 있는지에 대한 제 생각을 바꿨습니다.
because before it was just mostly
이전에는 대부분 게임에
games like the [INAUDIBLE].
국한되었기 때문입니다.
In games, there's a lot of--
게임에서는 가능한 한
you can just spawn as many games as possible.
많은 게임을 생성할 수 있습니다.
But for the real world, there's always sim-to-real gap,
하지만 실제 세계에서는 항상 시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 격차가
where you are training on the same game,
존재합니다. 동일한 게임에서 훈련하고
you are also testing on the same game.
동일한 게임에서 테스트합니다.
But for robots, if you train on a simulation,
하지만 로봇의 경우, 시뮬레이션에서 훈련하면
how much does the sim-to-real gap matters for the agents
시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 격차가 실제 환경에
to generalize to the real environments?
일반화하는 데 얼마나 중요한가요?
And this paper really convinced me
이 논문은 때때로 시뮬레이션과 실제
that, sometimes, the sim-to-real gap just
간의 격차가 그리 중요하지 않을 수 있다는
may not matter that much.
것을 저에게 확신시켰습니다.
So we are not simulating the bushes.
따라서 우리는 덤불을 시뮬레이션하고 있지 않습니다.
We are not simulating the snows.
우리는 눈을 시뮬레이션하고 있는 것이 아닙니다.
But the agents that's using reinforcement learning,
하지만 강화 학습을 사용하는 에이전트는
that training simulation, can give you
이러한 훈련 시뮬레이션을
some very, very robust performance
통해 실제 물리적
in the real physical world, like snows and [INAUDIBLE] very, very
세계에서 매우 강력한 성능을 발휘할 수 있습니다. 예를 들어
slippery surface.
눈이나 매우 미끄러운 표면에서요.
On the right is a very recent video
오른쪽은 Unitree에서
released by Unitree that shows just another level of dexterity
최근에 발표한 비디오로, 시뮬레이션에서 실제로 전이할 수
for locomotions that can do this sim-to-real transfer,
있는 이동성의 또 다른 수준을 보여줍니다. 이
allow these robots to do very, very crazy
로봇들은 매우 미친 듯이 역동적인
and dynamic behaviors.
행동을 할 수 있습니다.
They can navigate into some very rough and challenging terrains.
그들은 매우 거칠고 도전적인 지형을 탐색할 수 있습니다.
I would say, in the domain of robot locomotion,
로봇 이동성 분야에서는 거의 해결된
it is close to be a solved problem.
문제에 가깝다고 할 수 있습니다.
And the solution to this problem is exactly
이 문제의 해결책은 바로 강화
reinforcement learning.
학습입니다.
So this is about locomotion.
이것은 이동성에 관한 것입니다.
So other domain is about manipulations or the robot
다른 분야는 조작에 관한 것으로, 로봇이
has to manipulate the objects in the real physical world.
실제 물리적 세계에서 물체를 조작해야 합니다.
So in 2019, when OpenAI was still like--
2019년, OpenAI가 로봇 공학에 대해
touch upon robotics, they designed the systems
다루고 있을 때, 그들은 루빅스 큐브의 능숙한
that are trying to do dexterous manipulations of Rubik's cube.
조작을 시도하는 시스템을 설계했습니다.
They are able to do the reinforcement learning
그들은 시뮬레이션에서 강화 학습을
in simulation and do sim-to-real transfer that
수행하고, 이러한 로봇들이 루빅스 큐브를
allows these kind of robots to solve this Rubik's cube.
해결할 수 있도록 하는 시뮬레이션에서 실제로 전이할 수 있습니다.
But one caveat is that their success rate is very, very low.
하지만 한 가지 주의할 점은 그들의 성공률이 매우 낮다는 것입니다.
Although these videos seem to be very beautifully done,
이 비디오들이 매우 아름답게 제작된 것처럼
but their success rate was very low.
보이지만, 그들의 성공률은 매우 낮았습니다.
And if you really look at the papers,
그리고 논문을 자세히 살펴보면,
they only tested a very limited amount of trials.
그들은 매우 제한된 수의 실험만을 수행했습니다.
And given that number, possibly the reliability
그 숫자를 고려할 때, 신뢰성이 그리
is not very satisfying.
만족스럽지 않을 수 있습니다.
But still, since then, people have
하지만 그 이후로
been able to extend upon this dexterous manipulation problems
사람들은 이러한 능숙한 조작 문제를
and allow the robots to do enhanced dexterous manipulation
확장하여 로봇들이 다양한 유형의
and reorientations of different types of objects
물체를 향상된 능숙한 조작과
and into different target configurations.
재배치할 수 있도록 했습니다.
It's all thanks to the developments of reinforcement
모두 강화 학습의 발전
learning.
덕분입니다.
But we can see, until now, our examples in locomotions
하지만 지금까지의 이동성과 손 조작의 예를 보면, 그들에게
and in hand manipulation, it doesn't really
문제를 해결하지는 못하지만,
solve the problem for them, but if the robot can just
로봇이 당신을 위해
fold the clothes for you or do the laundry for you
옷을 개거나 세탁을 해줄
in your home.
수 있다면 좋겠습니다.
For manipulation, still in this kind of very isolated domains,
조작의 경우, 여전히 이러한 고립된 환경에서
like working with this kind of isolated environments.
작업하는 것과 같은 매우 제한된 영역에 있습니다.
So this is actually some of the key challenges and bottlenecks
이것은 기존의 모델 없는 강화 학습의 주요
of existing model-free reinforcement learning.
도전 과제와 병목 현상 중 일부입니다.
It is mostly learned from the trials and error
주로 환경과의 시행착오를
with the environments, and it requires extensive interactions
통해 학습하며, 세계와의 광범위한 상호작용이
with the world.
필요합니다.
For example, for the AlphaGo Zero,
예를 들어, AlphaGo Zero는
it actually learns from 3,000 years of human knowledge in 40
40일 동안 3,000년의 인간 지식으로부터 학습합니다.
days, which is amazing.
이는 놀랍습니다.
But it still requires many, many years
하지만 여전히 에이전트가 학습하기
of computation, years of equivalent computations
위해서는 수년의 계산이
for the agents to learn.
필요합니다.
If in domains where there's a huge sim-to-real gap
시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 큰 격차가 있는
and you want to do the reinforcement learning
분야에서 실제 물리적 세계에서 강화
in the real physical world, that will be a huge bottleneck
학습을 수행하고자 한다면, 이는 강화 학습 에이전트를
for learning this reinforcement learning agents
매우 효과적으로 학습하는 데 큰
very effectively.
병목 현상이 될 것입니다.
And also, of course, if there is sim-to-real gap, if you only
물론, 시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 격차가 있다면,
can learn the model in the real environments,
실제 환경에서만 모델을 학습할 수
there's a lot of safety concerns.
있다면 많은 안전 문제가 발생합니다.
For example, here is an example showing
예를 들어, 여기에는 이러한 휴머노이드
this kind of learning progressions
로봇이 앞으로 이동하도록
of an agent that is controlling these humanoid robots to move
제어하는 에이전트의 학습 진행 상황을 보여주는
forwards.
예가 있습니다.
You can see that during this learning
이 학습 과정에서
process, although at the very end,
로봇이 결국 앞으로
the robot is able to move forwards,
이동할 수 있지만, 매우 이상한
but there's a lot of very weird behaviors
행동이 많이 발생하는 것을 볼
that you can totally imagine if you apply
수 있습니다. 이 에이전트를
this agent on the real physical robots,
실제 로봇에 적용하면 재앙적으로
it will fail catastrophically.
실패할 것이라고 상상할 수 있습니다.
And it also have a very limited interpretabilities.
그리고 해석 가능성도 매우 제한적입니다.
And sometimes, it's very hard to correct things
때때로, 일이 잘못될 때
when things go wrong.
수정하기가 매우 어렵습니다.
And one interesting thing, if you really
흥미로운 점은, 인간이 환경과
think about how humans learn to interact
상호작용하는 방법과 순수한
with the environment versus pure reinforcement learning,
강화 학습을 생각해보면, 우리는 이
you realize that we humans have a very intuitive understanding
환경에 대한 매우 직관적인 이해를 가지고
of this environment.
있다는 것입니다.
We can imagine how the environment
우리는 특정 행동을 적용할
is going to change if we apply a specific action.
경우 환경이 어떻게 변화할지를 상상할 수 있습니다.
So it's exactly this predictive capabilities
바로 이러한 예측 능력이 우리가
that allows we, humans, to plan our behavior in achieving
특정 목표를 달성하기 위해 행동을 계획할
some specific targets.
수 있게 해줍니다.
And this predictive capabilities is also actually learned
이러한 예측 능력은 실제 물리적
from we human's physical interactions
세계와의 인간의 물리적
and everyday experiences with the real physical world.
상호작용과 일상적인 경험에서 학습된 것입니다.
So going beyond the reinforcement learning,
강화 학습을 넘어,
the next topic I want to discuss will
제가 논의하고 싶은 다음 주제는 로봇이
be how we can endow the robots with similar capabilities
자신의 행동의 결과를 상상하고 모델 기반 계획을
in imagining the effect of their actions
수행할 수 있는 유사한 능력을
and to do model-based planning.
부여하는 방법입니다.
For the specific examples, we have a simulation.
구체적인 예로, 우리는 시뮬레이션을 가지고 있습니다.
Typically, the simulation people use would be, for example,
일반적으로 사람들이 사용하는 시뮬레이션은 NVIDIA에서
Isaac Gym or Isaac Sim developed by NVIDIA.
개발한 Isaac Gym 또는 Isaac Sim과 같은 것입니다.
And there are essentially a bunch of rigid body simulations
본질적으로 로봇이 바닥의 표현과
where the robot's just touching this kind of a polygon
같은 다각형 형태의 표현에
type of representation, like a representation of the floor.
접촉하는 강체 시뮬레이션이 있습니다.
It is not simulating, for example, the bushes.
예를 들어, 덤불을 시뮬레이션하지 않습니다.
It is not simulating those snows.
눈을 시뮬레이션하지 않습니다.
But what people do is to randomize
하지만 사람들이 하는 것은
the simulated environments a lot and randomize
시뮬레이션된 환경을 많이 무작위화하고
the friction, the geometry, and many other physical parameters
마찰, 기하학 및 이 환경 내의 많은 다른
inside this environment such that people will assume whatever
물리적 매개변수를 무작위화하여 사람들이 실제 물리적 세계에서
you encounter in the real physical world is just one data
만나는 것은 시뮬레이션 내에서 무작위화한 분포
point within the distributions you
내의 하나의 데이터 포인트라고
randomize within your simulation.
가정하게 만드는 것입니다.
So if your policies can be robust,
따라서 정책이 그 분포 내에서 로봇을
robust in controlling this robots within that distribution,
제어하는 데 강력할 수 있고, 실제 세계가
and if the real world is just one data
그 분포 내의 하나의 데이터
point within that distribution, the policy can generalize.
포인트라면 정책은 일반화할 수 있습니다.
And so far, at least from this empirical evidence,
지금까지 이 경험적 증거에 따르면, 이러한
this type of assumption actually holds,
유형의 가정은 실제로 성립하며,
and the policy actually works very reliably and robustly
정책은 실제 물리적 세계에서 매우 신뢰할
in the real physical world.
수 있고 강력하게 작동합니다.
So the question is about, what is the actual command?
그래서 질문은 실제 명령이 무엇인가입니다.
So actually, in many of the existing demos,
실제로 많은 기존 데모에서는 사람이
there can be a person providing high-level commands
로봇에 고수준 명령을 제공할 수
to the robot.
있습니다.
For example, which direction should the robots walk?
예를 들어, 로봇이 어떤 방향으로 걸어야 하는지입니다.
So the robot rotates in place or just still keep
그래서 로봇은 제자리에서 회전하거나 계속
walking forwards.
앞으로 걸어갑니다.
Conditioned on that high-level actions provided by human,
사람이 제공한 고수준 행동에 따라 로봇은 이러한
the robot has to decide this kind of low-level actions.
저수준 행동을 결정해야 합니다.
The low-level actions are typically,
저수준 행동은
for example, the joint torque that
일반적으로 이 로봇의 모든 관절에
are applied to each and every one of the joints
적용되는 관절 토크와
on top of this robot.
같은 것입니다.
So that is how this typically looks
이것이 일반적으로 어떻게 보이는지를 의미하며,
like, meaning humans give high-level commands,
인간이 고수준 명령, 조건부 고수준
conditional high-level commands.
명령을 제공합니다.
The robot has to use this policy to decide
로봇은 이 정책을 사용하여
this kind of low-level actions, which is instantiated
관절 토크를 사용하여 구현되는 저수준
using joint torque.
행동을 결정해야 합니다.
So like I mentioned, one biggest lesson I
제가 언급했듯이, 이 보행 작업에서 배운 가장
learned from this line of work on locomotion
큰 교훈 중 하나는 시뮬레이션이 완벽할
is that the simulation doesn't have to be perfect.
필요는 없다는 것입니다.
As long as you randomize it enough,
충분히 무작위화하기만 하면
it can generalize very robustly in the real environments.
실제 환경에서 매우 강력하게 일반화할 수 있습니다.
But such lesson hasn't really been generalized very well
하지만 이러한 교훈은 조작 영역에서 잘
in the manipulation domain.
일반화되지 않았습니다.
So in the manipulation domain, how accurate the simulation
조작 영역에서 시뮬레이션이 얼마나 정확해야
needs to be and how much does the sim-to-real gap
하는지와 시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 차이가 얼마나
matters is still a research question people hope to answer.
중요한지는 여전히 사람들이 답하고자 하는 연구 질문입니다.
So I can give you one specific example.
하나의 구체적인 예를 드릴 수 있습니다.
If in the simulation you are pushing a box forwards,
시뮬레이션에서 상자를 앞으로 밀고 있을 때,
if in simulation, the box rotates for 10 degrees
시뮬레이션에서 상자가 10도 회전하지만
but in reality it rotates for 12 degrees,
실제로는 12도 회전한다면, 그리
it may not matter that much.
중요하지 않을 수 있습니다.
But if in the real world, your grasping was successful.
하지만 실제 세계에서 당신의 잡기가 성공적이었다면.
But in simulation, the object just
그러나 시뮬레이션에서는 물체가 어떤
flies away because of some kind of numerical issues.
수치적 문제로 인해 그냥 날아가 버립니다.
Or if the object slips away between your fingers,
또는 물체가 손가락 사이에서 미끄러져
that's problematic.
나간다면, 이는 문제가 됩니다.
So there are regions where sim-to-real gap matter.
따라서 시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 차이가 중요한 영역이 있습니다.
There are other regions sim-to-real gap may not
조작 영역에서는 시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 차이가
matter that much in the manipulation domain.
그리 중요하지 않을 수 있는 다른 영역도 있습니다.
And people still are trying to answer
사람들은 여전히 시뮬레이션과
and trying to understand how sim-to-real gap can happen
실제 간의 차이가 어떻게 발생할 수 있는지, 그리고 가장 신뢰할
and what are some of the most important recipes
수 있는 시뮬레이션-실제 전이를 위해
and characteristics that this simulation needs
이 시뮬레이션이 가져야 할 가장
to have for the most reliable sim-to-real transfer.
중요한 레시피와 특성이 무엇인지 이해하려고 노력하고 있습니다.
So If I understand your questions correctly,
그래서 제가 당신의 질문을 올바르게
you are asking--
이해했다면, 여전히
there are still a person providing high-level commands
사람이 로봇에 고수준 명령을 제공하고 있다는
to the robots.
것입니다.
So the question is, can the robot
그래서 질문은 로봇이 인간보다
come up with better plans than the human?
더 나은 계획을 세울 수 있는가입니다.
So I can actually give you a more nuanced perspective.
그래서 저는 실제로 더 미묘한 관점을 제공할 수 있습니다.
Although many of these videos seems very nice,
이 비디오들이 매우 멋져
there is a human operator operating the robots
보이지만, 로봇이 어떤 경로를 선택할지
to choose which route to go.
결정하는 인간 조작자가 있습니다.
For example, what people typically do is-- for example,
예를 들어, 사람들이 일반적으로 하는 것은
let's say, there's some kind of rough terrains
거칠거나 바위 더미가 있는
or some pile of rocks.
지형을 가정하는 것입니다.
And the humans can actually try to command the robot
인간은 실제로 로봇에게 앞으로 나아가고 그 바위를
to go forward, trying to climb those kind of rocks.
오르도록 명령할 수 있습니다.
If that fails, humans can actually
이것이 실패하면, 인간은 바위
provide some other high-level commands to get around
더미를 피하기 위한 다른 고급 명령을
this pile of rocks.
제공할 수 있습니다.
So there can be some kind of learning also
따라서 로봇의 능력을 이해하는
on the human side in understanding the capabilities
데 있어 인간 측에서도 어떤
of those robots.
학습이 있을 수 있습니다.
So this is also why some of this video
이것이 일부 비디오가 매우 멋져 보일
can actually look very nice because humans select the routes
수 있는 이유이기도 합니다. 왜냐하면 인간이 알고 있는
that the human knows can show the limits and also
경로를 선택하여 이러한 저수준 제어기의
the capabilities of this kind of low-level controllers.
한계와 능력을 보여주기 때문입니다.
And how to do that autonomously?
그렇다면 이를 자율적으로 어떻게 할 수 있을까요?
That's actually a very interesting question
사람들이 연구하고 있는 매우
people are also doing research upon.
흥미로운 질문입니다.
So then I'm going to continue.
그럼 계속하겠습니다.
So I've discussed some of the successful examples and power
저는 강화 학습의 성공적인 사례와 힘에 대해
of reinforcement learning and also
논의했으며, 강화 학습의
discussed the limitations of reinforcement learning.
한계에 대해서도 논의했습니다.
And we still haven't really seen very, very successful
그리고 우리는 아직 조작에서 강화
and wide-scale deployments of reinforcement
학습의 매우 성공적이고 대규모
learning in manipulation yet.
배포를 보지 못했습니다.
And we, humans, not just learn from trials and error.
우리는 인간이 단순히 시행착오로 배우지 않습니다.
We actually build this type of internal model.
우리는 실제로 이러한 내부 모델을 구축합니다.
So we're asking the question, can we actually learn
그래서 우리는 로봇이 환경과
the models from the robot's interactions
상호작용하면서 모델을 학습하고, 그 모델을
with the environments and using that model for the robot to do
사용하여 로봇이 더 나은 물리적 상호작용을
better physical interactions?
할 수 있을지 질문하고 있습니다.
So specifically, what we are touching upon, again, back
구체적으로, 우리가 다시 이 그림을
to this figure, is how we can learn
언급하는 것은 우리가 실제
and approximations of the real physical world,
물리적 세계를 어떻게 학습하고 근사할 수 있는지,
and how can this approximated physical world
그리고 이 근사된 물리적 세계가 가상 도메인에서
that runs on the virtual domain can help
어떻게 로봇의 행동을 안내하고 물리적
guide the robot's actions and decide what action
세계에서 어떤 행동을 취할지를
to take in the physical world?
결정하는 데 도움이 될 수 있는지입니다.
So let's say, if you already have the model,
예를 들어, 이미 모델이
for example, let's say, you have already learned the models
있다고 가정해 보겠습니다. 예를
like we humans have in our mental environments,
들어, 우리가 인간처럼 정신적 환경에서 모델을 이미
we can predict, given the current state st
학습했다면, 현재 상태 st와 행동
and also the action t, how the state of the environment
t를 주었을 때 환경의 상태가 t+1
will change into states t plus 1.
상태로 어떻게 변화할지를 예측할 수 있습니다.
And then we can use this, essentially,
그리고 우리는 이것을 본질적으로 현재
as a forward model that, given the current state and action,
상태와 행동을 주어 다음 상태를 예측하는 전방
predict the next state.
모델로 사용할 수 있습니다.
So what actually is the problem for us
그렇다면 우리가 계획을 세우는 데
to do the planning, which is essentially
있어 문제는 무엇일까요? 이는
an inverse of this forward model?
본질적으로 이 전방 모델의 역입니다.
Well, the planning is to give the current state and the target
계획은 현재 상태와 목표 상태를
states and to come up with the action that can allow the robot
주고 로봇이 목표 상태를 달성할 수 있도록
to achieve the target states.
하는 행동을 제시하는 것입니다.
Given the current state shown in the blue dots,
파란 점으로 표시된 현재 상태를 고려할
we have the targets shown in the red.
때, 빨간 점으로 표시된 목표가 있습니다.
We can have maybe some initial guesses of how
행동이 어떻게 보일지에 대한 초기
the actions might look like.
추측을 할 수 있습니다.
And our model, our approximated learned models,
우리의 모델, 즉 근사된 학습
will be able to predict the sequence
모델은 상태의 순차적
evolutions of the states, which is
진화를 예측할 수 있으며,
shown in this green trajectory.
이는 이 녹색 궤적에 나타납니다.
And then we can measure the distance between this green dots
그런 다음 이 녹색 점과 빨간 점
and the red dots and backpropagates
사이의 거리를 측정하고, 궤적을
or doing optimizations using the gradients of their distance
따라 모든 행동에 대한 거리의 기울기를 사용하여 역전파하거나
with respect to all the actions along the trajectories
최적화를 수행하여 이러한 유형의
to do this type of optimizations,
최적화를 수행하여
in order to know what actions can guide us
빨간 점으로 표시된 목표에 더
to getting us closer to the targets shown in the red.
가까워질 수 있는 행동을 알 수 있습니다.
And obviously, the model may not be accurate enough,
명백히도 모델이 충분히 정확하지 않을 수
so we typically only executes the first actions,
있으므로, 우리는 일반적으로 첫 번째 행동만
and we obtain the new states from the environment.
실행하고 환경에서 새로운 상태를 얻습니다.
And we can re-optimize the action sequence using
그리고 우리는 경량 하강법이나
gradient descent or any other optimization
다른 최적화 기술을
techniques you use to do this trajectory optimizations.
사용하여 행동 시퀀스를 다시 최적화할 수 있습니다.
And one of the key benefits, especially recently
특히 최근 GPU와 신경 동역학 모델의
with the development of GPUs and also neural dynamics model,
발전으로 인해, GPU를 사용하여
is that you can use the GPU for parallel
대규모 샘플링 및 행동
and simultaneously sampling to allow
시퀀스의 최적화를 수행할
you to do large-scale sampling and optimizations
수 있는 병렬 및 동시
of those action sequences, which is actually quite efficient.
샘플링이 가능하다는 것이 주요 이점 중 하나입니다.
So given this, the general framework,
따라서 이를 고려할 때, 일반적인
you have the model, which is this kind of forward process.
프레임워크는 모델이 이 전방 프로세스라는 것입니다.
And you can always use the forward model
그리고 항상 이 전방 모델을
to do this inverse optimizations to come up
사용하여 이러한 역 최적화를 수행하여
with the actions that can get you closer to your target
목표 구성에 더 가까워질 수 있는 행동을
configuration.
제시할 수 있습니다.
And one of the key questions has always
그리고 항상 중요한 질문 중 하나는
been, what should be the right representation
환경의 올바른 표현이 무엇이어야
of the environment?
하는가입니다.
What should be the right and most effective
올바르고 가장 효과적인 상태 표현
state representation s?
s는 무엇이어야 하는가?
And how we can learn this model based
그리고 상태 표현을 기반으로 이
on the state representation.
모델을 어떻게 학습할 수 있는가.
And over the years, there has been
수년 동안 다양한
many different investigations on choosing or investigating
상태 표현을 선택하거나 조사하는
different types of state representations.
다양한 연구가 있었습니다.
Some earlier work, including how can using, for example,
이전 작업 중 일부는 예를 들어 2D
just 2D images as a representation of the states
이미지를 상태의 표현으로 사용하고 픽셀 동역학을
and trying to learn pixel dynamics,
학습하는 방법에 관한 것입니다. 즉,
meaning how the image might change if you apply a specific
특정 행동을 적용했을 때 이미지가 어떻게 변할 수 있는지를
action.
의미합니다.
This is a work called deep visual foresight, which
이 작업은 딥 비주얼 포어사이트라고
set off some of the initial works
하며, 전체 단어 모델
in the whole domains of word models.
영역에서 초기 작업 중 일부를 시작했습니다.
And by learning this kind of pixel-based dynamics models,
이러한 픽셀 기반 동역학 모델을
people can come up with strategies
학습함으로써 사람들은
that is able to, for example, minimize
현재 관찰과 초록색으로
the distance between the current observations and some
표시된 목표 간의 거리를
can rotate the objects and push the objects around in order
최소화하고, 물체를 회전시키고
to achieve the targets shown in green,
밀어내는 전략을 고안할 수 있습니다.
and the current state is shown in red.
현재 상태는 빨간색으로 표시됩니다.
So this is about pixel dynamics.
이것은 픽셀 동역학에 관한 것입니다.
And what people can also do is to use keypoints
사람들이 할 수 있는 또 다른 방법은 환경의
as a representation of the environments
표현으로 키포인트를 사용하여
to learn keypoints dynamics models.
키포인트 동역학 모델을 학습하는 것입니다.
And here, what we can do is to track the movement
여기서 우리는 이 상자 위의 키포인트의
of the keypoints on top of this box over the 3D space and also
움직임을 3D 공간에서 추적하고, 특정 밀기 행동의 결과로서
neural dynamics model of those keypoints as a result of some
이러한 키포인트의 신경 동역학 모델을 추적할
pushing actions.
수 있습니다.
And then we can allow the robots to use
그런 다음 로봇이 이러한 전방
this forward predictive models to plan the robot's behaviors
예측 모델을 사용하여 특정 궤적을 추적하고
to track some specific trajectories in order
이 상자를 밀어 목표
to push this box to achieve our target configurations.
구성을 달성하도록 로봇의 행동을 계획할 수 있습니다.
So besides using keypoints, so what
키포인트를 사용하는 것
if you encountered some objects with even higher degrees
외에, 더 높은 자유도를 가진 물체를 만난다면
of freedom?
어떻게 될까요?
So if you go one level finer, you
한 단계 더 세분화하면, 이러한
can also represent those objects using a set of particles,
물체를 본질적으로 점의 집합인 입자의 집합으로
essentially a set of points.
표현할 수 있습니다.
Here, which is actually a work that
여기서, 제가 박사후 연구원으로
was done while I was here as a postdoc,
있을 때 수행한 작업으로,
we were representing this pile of granular pieces,
우리는 이 입자들의 집합을
using a bunch of particles and trying
사용하여 이 입자들이
to predict how those particles will move around
특정 행동을 적용했을 때 어떻게
if you apply a specific action.
움직일지를 예측하려고 했습니다.
And this forward model can allow the robots
이 전방 모델은 로봇이
to do this inverse decision making that
다양한 크기의 입자 물체를
handle a wide range of granular objects
처리하는 역 결정 만들기를
of different granular sizes.
수행할 수 있게 합니다.
And we come up with strategies that
우리는 이러한 조각들을
can gather those pieces into the target
오른쪽 하단에 표시된 목표 영역으로
region shown in the bottom right,
모으는 전략을 고안했습니다. 각
like a corner of each segment.
세그먼트의 모서리와 같은 곳입니다.
And the same model with good feedback from the environments
환경으로부터의 좋은 피드백을 받는 동일한 모델은
allow the robots to correct from the model's error
로봇이 모델의 오류를 수정하고 모든 물체
and come up with strategies that can be very reliably aggregate
조각을 목표 영역으로 매우 신뢰성 있게
all the object pieces into the target region.
집합할 수 있는 전략을 고안할 수 있게 합니다.
And obviously, this model not just
분명히 이 모델은
can generalize to different granular pieces
서로 다른 크기의 다양한 입자 조각에
of different granular sizes.
일반화할 수 있습니다.
It can also change to different target configurations.
또한 서로 다른 목표 구성으로 변경할 수 있습니다.
Here, you will very quickly realize what
여기서 여러분은 목표 구성이
the target configurations are.
무엇인지 매우 빠르게 깨닫게 될 것입니다.
The robot has to come up with a strategy that
로봇은 미세한 조각의 비트리비얼
to do nontrivial redistributions of the granular pieces.
재분배를 수행할 전략을 세워야 합니다.
And after the redistribution, it has
재분배 후에는 형태와 같은
to align the fine-grained details
목표에 맞춰 세밀한 세부
with the targets like shape.
사항을 정렬해야 합니다.
You want to accomplish this like a pile rearrangement task.
이것을 더미 재배치 작업처럼 수행하고 싶습니다.
The task here is actually to rearrange this granular pieces
여기서의 작업은 이 미세한 조각들을
into different letter shapes, all the way from letter A
A자에서 Z자까지 다양한
to letter Z. And with this kind of forward models,
문자 형태로 재배치하는 것입니다. 이러한 종류의 전방 모델을 통해 우리는
we'll be very successful in coming up
환경의 피드백을 받아 로봇이
with a sequence of strategies, of course,
이러한 물체 조각들을 목표
with feedback from the environments
지역으로 재배치할 수
to allow the robot to rearrange this kind of object pieces
있는 일련의 전략을 성공적으로 개발할
into the target regions.
수 있습니다.
And this is actually a highly nontrivial task.
이것은 실제로 매우 비트리비얼한 작업입니다.
And going beyond that, we also have this subsequent work,
그것을 넘어, 저는 여기 스탠포드에 있을 때
which I was also involved and done
참여하고 수행한
when I was here at Stanford.
후속 작업도 있습니다.
And we designed this kind of dumpling-making robots, that is,
우리는 15개의 서로 다른 3D
actually equipped the robots with 15 different 3D-printed
프린트 도구를 장착한 만두 제조 로봇을
tools.
설계했습니다.
We have four RGBD cameras looking at the environment
우리는 환경을 관찰하여 매장의 기하학을 재구성하기
to do a reconstruction of the geometry of the store.
위해 4개의 RGBD 카메라를 사용합니다.
And the robots will have to decide what tool to use
로봇은 어떤 도구를 사용할지,
and what action to take to get this dumpling into--
이 반죽을 만두로 만들기 위해 어떤 행동을
getting this dough into a dumpling.
취할지를 결정해야 합니다.
And the key enabling factor is also
핵심 요소는
this forward predictive models represented using particles.
입자를 사용하여 표현된 이러한 전방 예측 모델입니다.
Or here, the red dots are representing
여기서 빨간 점은 도구의 형태를
the shape of the tool, and the blue dots
나타내고, 파란
are representing the shape of the objects.
점은 물체의 형태를 나타냅니다.
The first row is our model's open loop prediction,
첫 번째 행은 우리의 모델의 개방 루프
and second row is what actually happens in the real environment.
예측이고, 두 번째 행은 실제 환경에서 발생하는 일입니다.
So this learned model that directly learns
이 학습된 모델은 실제 세계의
from this real-world interactions
상호작용에서 직접 학습하여 다양한
can very accurately predict the change of the shape of the dough
도구를 사용하고 다양한 행동을 적용할 때 반죽의
when using different tools, applying different actions,
형태 변화에 대해 매우 정확하게
and in the end allows us to have this integrated system that can
예측할 수 있으며, 결국 반죽으로 만두를 만들 수 있는
make a dumpling out of a dough.
통합 시스템을 제공합니다.
What's interesting about this video
이 비디오에서 흥미로운
is there's a person constantly perturbing
점은 누군가가 로봇이 작업을 수행하는
the robot from doing its job.
것을 지속적으로 방해하고 있다는 것입니다.
The robot will take the real-time visual feedback
로봇은 이 환경에서 실시간 시각적 피드백을
from this environment to real-time
받아 반죽의 형태를
understanding the shape of the dough
실시간으로 이해하고, 현재 관찰과
and then using the current observations and also
환경 변화 예측을 위한 학습된 동역학
the learned dynamics model that predicts how the environment is
모델을 사용하여 도구를 사용해
going to change, how the dose shape will
특정 행동을 적용할
change if you use a tool to apply a specific action,
경우 반죽의 형태가 어떻게 변할지를
and, based on this forward model,
예측하며, 이 전방 모델을
is making this inverse decision.
기반으로 역결정을 내립니다.
This decision is happening at two levels,
이 결정은 두 가지 수준에서
both at the high level, which is to decide
이루어지며, 높은 수준에서는 어떤 도구를 사용할지
what tool to use, which is a task-level decision making.
결정하는 작업 수준의 의사결정이 포함됩니다.
And given these tools, the robot also
그리고 이러한 도구를 고려할 때,
have to make a lower-level, emotion-level decisions
로봇은 다음 작업 단계로 진행하기 위해
in deciding what specific action to take in order to progress
어떤 특정 행동을 취할지를 결정하는 낮은 수준의
into the next task stage.
감정적 결정을 내려야 합니다.
Humans are just so annoying, adding pieces, folding
인간은 정말 성가십니다. 조각을 추가하고 반죽을
the dough.
접습니다.
The robot is very robust to this external disturbance
로봇은 작업을 수행하는 데 있어 이러한
in continuing its progress in doing the task.
외부 방해에 매우 강인합니다.
Here's what's interesting.
여기서 흥미로운 점은.
After the robot casts a circle, the human shows no mercy,
로봇이 원을 그린 후, 인간은 자비 없이 모든
destroys everything.
것을 파괴합니다.
The robot knows you actually have
로봇은 실제로 처음부터
to start from the very beginning,
다시 시작해야 하며, 이러한
redo the task from the beginning in order
작업 목표를 진행하기 위해 처음부터
to progress with this kind of task objective.
작업을 다시 수행해야 한다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So this really shows the patience and also
이것은 외부 방해에 대한
the robustness of our systems with this type
우리의 시스템의 인내와 강인함을
of external disturbance.
보여줍니다.
And all of these capabilities is enabled
이 모든 능력은 특정 행동을 적용할
by this kind of neural dynamics model that
경우 반죽의 형태가 어떻게
predicts how the shape of the dough
변화할지를 예측하는
will change if you apply a specific action.
신경 역학 모델에 의해 가능해집니다.
In the end, the robot will place the skin
결국 로봇은 이 만두 클립
on top of this dumpling clip and move this kind of fillings
위에 피를 놓고, 이 만두 피 위에
on top of this dumpling skin and use a hook
속을 옮기고, 훅을 사용하여
to close the dumpling clip in order
만두 클립을 닫아
to use this general purpose robot equipped
15개의 다목적 도구가 장착된
with 15 general purpose tools to make a dumpling out of a dough.
이 일반 목적 로봇을 사용하여 반죽으로 만두를 만듭니다.
So this is about how we can learn the model
이것은 우리가 모델을 어떻게
and how that model can be useful for downstream model-based
학습하고 그 모델이 하류 모델 기반 계획에 어떻게 유용할 수
planning.
있는지에 관한 것입니다.
So for this specific case, if we want
따라서 이 특정 경우에 대해 더 엄밀하게 설명하고자
to describe it more rigorously, we
한다면, 우리는 강화
are not using reinforcement learning.
학습을 사용하지 않습니다.
We just learn the model and use that model to do planning,
우리는 단순히 모델을 학습하고 그 모델을 사용하여
although the plan can be distilled into a policy that
계획을 세우지만, 그 계획은 실제 환경에서
can be executed in the real environment in a more
보다 효율적으로 실행할 수 있는 정책으로
efficient manner.
정제될 수 있습니다.
But some people also call it model-based reinforcement
하지만 일부 사람들은 이것을 모델 기반 강화 학습이라고도
learning.
부릅니다.
Decide which background you are coming from.
어떤 배경에서 오는지 결정하세요.
You can either call it model learning
모델 학습 및 모델 기반 계획이라고
and model-based planning.
부를 수 있습니다.
You can also call it model-based reinforcement learning.
모델 기반 강화 학습이라고 부를 수도 있습니다.
But the key idea is you want to learn the model from the robot's
하지만 핵심 아이디어는 로봇이 실제 물리적 세계와의
physical interactions with the real physical world
물리적 상호작용을 통해 모델을
and using that learned model that
학습하고, 그 학습된
is very effective in helping the robot
모델이 로봇이 작업 목표를
to decide its behaviors to progress with the task
진행하기 위한 행동을 결정하는 데 매우
objective.
효과적이라는 것입니다.
So in this specific case, the high-level planning
따라서 이 특정 경우에 높은 수준의 계획과 낮은
and low-level decision making is done by two different models.
수준의 의사결정은 두 개의 서로 다른 모델에 의해 수행됩니다.
So over the high level, we are given the current state,
높은 수준에서는 현재 상태, 환경의 현재 관찰
current observation of the environments and the target's
및 로봇이 달성할 수 있는 목표가
the robot able to achieve, essentially
주어지며, 본질적으로
a classifier that classify which tool to use.
어떤 도구를 사용할지를 분류하는 분류기입니다.
And conditional on this classifier, tool label,
그리고 이 분류기, 도구 레이블에 조건부로,
this is a low-level policy that decides
이는 다음 작업 단계로 진행하기
what specific action to take in order to progress
위해 어떤 특정 행동을 취할지를
into the next task stage.
결정하는 낮은 수준의 정책입니다.
Very good question.
아주 좋은 질문입니다.
So back then, this work was done in 2023.
그 당시 이 작업은 2023년에 수행되었습니다.
At that time, visual language model wasn't very powerful.
그때 시각 언어 모델은 그리 강력하지 않았습니다.
So at that time, what we did was to allow a human operator
그래서 그때 우리가 한 것은 인간 운영자가 10번
to do the data collection, demonstration
작업을 데이터 수집 및 시연하도록
of the task for 10 times.
허용하는 것이었습니다.
We use that data to train this kind of classifier
우리는 그 데이터를 사용하여 어떤 도구를 사용할지를
to classify what tool to use.
분류하는 분류기를 학습했습니다.
That allows us to actually jump back and forth over this chain.
그것은 우리가 실제로 이 체인에서 앞뒤로 이동할 수 있게 해줍니다.
Like I mentioned earlier, after the robot cuts a circle,
앞서 언급했듯이, 로봇이 원을 자른 후 인간이
the human destroys everything.
모든 것을 파괴합니다.
The robot knows to jump back to some earlier stages that
로봇은 외부 방해로부터 적절한 복구를
fits to its current observation in order
수행하기 위해 현재
to do the proper recovery from the external disturbances.
관찰에 맞는 이전 단계로 되돌아가야 한다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So in this specific case, what we have been doing
따라서 이 특정 경우에 우리가
is a combination of sampling-based trajectory
하고 있는 것은 샘플링 기반 궤적
optimization versus policy learning.
최적화와 정책 학습의 조합입니다.
So what we have been doing is to give the current state
우리가 하고 있는 것은 이 반죽의 현재 상태를
of this dough.
제공하는 것입니다.
We have our forward predictive models.
우리는 우리의 전방 예측 모델을 가지고 있습니다.
We'll be able to sample a bunch of actions and sample
우리는 여러 가지 행동을 샘플링하고
a bunch of tools to predict what is the evolutions
여러 가지 도구를 샘플링하여 그 반죽의 형태가 어떻게
of the shape of that dough.
진화할지를 예측할 수 있습니다.
And then we'll compare the model's prediction
그리고 나서 우리는 모델의 예측을
with the targets we hope to achieve,
우리가 달성하고자 하는 목표와 비교할 것입니다.
which is similar to what I showed earlier.
이는 제가 이전에 보여준 것과 유사합니다.
For example, our model predicts the shape of the dough
예를 들어, 우리 모델은 반죽의 형태가 이
will go into this green dots, but the target
초록 점으로 갈 것이라고 예측하지만, 목표는
is this red dots, while comparing their distance.
이 빨간 점이며, 그 거리를 비교합니다.
And then that allows us to select
그리고 이는 우리가 목표에
the most effective actions that can get us to the target
최대한 가깝게 도달할 수 있는 가장 효과적인 행동을
to be as close as possible.
선택할 수 있게 해줍니다.
And we can do a lot of samples like this.
우리는 이렇게 많은 샘플을 할 수 있습니다.
But sampling during the test time is very time-consuming.
하지만 테스트 시간 동안 샘플링하는 것은 매우 시간이 많이 소요됩니다.
So we do this type of sampling in an offline fashion, which
그래서 우리는 오프라인 방식으로 이러한 샘플링을 수행하여 데이터
gives us a data set.
세트를 제공합니다.
And we can use that data set to train a policy that can
그리고 우리는 그 데이터 세트를 사용하여
be inferred at a very, very--
테스트 시간 동안 매우 짧은 시간에
using a very short period of time
추론할 수 있는
to do the inference during the test time.
정책을 훈련할 수 있습니다.
There is still a neural network as the policies.
정책으로서 여전히 신경망이 있습니다.
Yeah.
네.
Although the policy is learned by distilling from our models
정책은 방대한 샘플에 대한 모델의
predictions over a huge amount of samples.
예측을 증류하여 학습됩니다.
For this specific work, there is no physics-based simulation
이 특정 작업에서는 물리 기반 시뮬레이션이 전혀
at all.
없습니다.
We actually have a baseline that uses a state-of-the-art
우리는 실제로 MPM(Material Point
deformable object simulator, which is called MPM,
Methods)라는 최첨단 변형 물체 시뮬레이터를
Material Point Methods.
사용하는 기준선을 가지고 있습니다.
What we realize is that even if we do very extensive system
우리가 깨달은 것은 매우 광범위한 시스템 식별을 수행하더라도,
identification, like estimating the parameters
즉 물리 기반 변형 물체
of those physics-based deformable object simulator,
시뮬레이터의 매개변수를 추정하더라도, 식별된
the identified model is noticeably less accurate
모델이 실제 세계 상호작용에서 직접 학습한
than the model that directly learned
모델보다 눈에 띄게 정확도가
from the real-world interactions.
떨어진다는 것입니다.
Like I showed earlier, for example,
제가 이전에 보여준 것처럼, 예를
the first row is our model's open loop prediction.
들어 첫 번째 행은 우리 모델의 개방 루프 예측입니다.
The second row is the ground truth.
두 번째 행은 실제 값입니다.
Our model's prediction aligns very well
우리 모델의 예측은 실제
with the ground truth, which is just
값과 매우 잘 일치하며,
much more accurate than whatever physics-based simulator is
이는 어떤 물리 기반 시뮬레이터보다 훨씬 더
out there.
정확합니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
So if there are no more questions, I will continue.
더 이상 질문이 없다면 계속하겠습니다.
So what do we have discussed in this kind of model learning
우리가 이 모델 학습에서 논의한 내용과 이
and how this learned model can be
학습된 모델이 하류 모델 기반 계획에
effective for the downstream model-based planning.
어떻게 효과적일 수 있는지에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
And next category of algorithms is imitation learning.
다음 알고리즘 범주는 모방 학습입니다.
So just to recap a little bit, we
간단히 요약하자면, 우리는 강화 학습에
discussed reinforcement learning.
대해 논의했습니다.
That is directly learning the policies
이는 환경과의 시행착오를
by doing trials and error with the environments, which
통해 정책을 직접 학습하는 것으로, 샘플
has a lot of troubles, for example, the sample efficiency,
효율성, 안전 문제 등 많은 문제를
the safety concerns.
가지고 있습니다.
And for the model learning, what we have been doing
모델 학습의 경우, 우리가
is actually forced back to the category
하고 있는 것은 실제로 환경의 진화를
of supervised learning, where we have the evolutions
가진 감독 학습 범주로 강제로 돌아가는
of the environments.
것입니다.
You use that data to do supervised
그 데이터를 사용하여 감독 학습을 수행하여
learning to train this model and using this model
이 모델을 훈련하고 이 모델을
to do model-based planning.
사용하여 모델 기반 계획을 수행합니다.
And instead of just using supervised
그리고 단순히 감독 학습을 사용하여
learning to train the model, people are also asking,
모델을 훈련하는 대신, 사람들은 정책에 대해서도
can we do supervised learning also for the policies?
감독 학습을 할 수 있는지 묻고 있습니다.
This is the general idea of imitation learning, meaning
이것이 모방 학습의 일반적인 아이디어로,
can we have a big data set that shows how a task needs
작업이 어떻게 수행되어야 하는지를 보여주는 대규모 데이터 세트를
to be done and using this data set
가지고 이 정책을 훈련할 수
to train this kind of policies?
있는지를 의미합니다.
I'm showing this figure again.
이 그림을 다시 보여주고 있습니다.
This is trying to learn this kind of policy,
이는 상태를 입력으로 받아
taking the states as inputs that predict the actions.
행동을 예측하는 정책을 학습하려고 합니다.
And all of this kind of learning signals and learning procedures
이 모든 학습 신호와 학습 절차는
are done through a large-scale collected data,
인간이 작업을 수행하는 방법을
from human demoing to the robots how a task needs to be done.
로봇에게 시연하는 대규모 수집 데이터로 수행됩니다.
So learning from demonstration is, of course, not new.
따라서 시연을 통한 학습은 물론 새로운 것이 아닙니다.
It has been investigated for decades.
수십 년 동안 조사되어 왔습니다.
It's also constantly how we human is actually
우리는 매우 어릴 때부터
learning to perform a lot of physical interactions
실제 세계에서 많은 신체적
or social activities in the real world,
상호작용이나 사회적 활동을 수행하는
since we are very, very young.
방법을 배우고 있습니다.
So one of the most earlier classic imitation
가장 초기의 고전적인 모방 학습 알고리즘
learning algorithms is called behavior cloning, essentially
중 하나는 행동 복제라고 불리며,
trying to learn this kind of mapping that maps currently
현재 관찰 o에서 행동 a로
from this observation o into the action a.
매핑하는 것을 배우려고 합니다.
And this policy is represented using this function
이 정책은 세타로 매개변수화된
pi parameterized by the theta.
함수 pi를 사용하여 표현됩니다.
So one of the key issues for behavior cloning
행동 복제의 주요 문제 중 하나는
is called cascading error because, like I mentioned,
연쇄 오류라고 불리며, 로봇 학습이나
the key difference between the robot learning
에이전트의 환경과의 상호작용의
or agents' interaction with the environment
주요 차이점은 이것이
is it is a sequential decision-making problem.
순차적 의사결정 문제라는 것입니다.
It differs from a typical supervised learning
이는 일반적인 컴퓨터 비전 도메인에서의
in the typical computer vision domain
감독 학습과 다르며,
in that your error can accumulate
오류가 시간이 지남에 따라
and be amplified over time.
누적되고 증폭될 수 있습니다.
Let's say, at the very beginning,
예를 들어, 처음에 매우
you made a very small error.
작은 오류를 범했다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
That small error can lead to a state that slightly
그 작은 오류는 모델을 훈련하는 데 사용된 데이터
deviates from the distribution of data
분포에서 약간 벗어난 상태로
used to train your model.
이어질 수 있습니다.
That will lead the policy to make an even larger error.
그것은 정책이 더 큰 오류를 범하게 할 것입니다.
And this error will be amplified over the temporal horizons.
그리고 이 오류는 시간의 경과에 따라 증폭됩니다.
That leads to a trajectory that can
그로 인해 시연 궤적과
deviate quite a lot from the demonstration trajectories.
많이 벗어난 궤적이 발생할 수 있습니다.
So that's the typical issues of behavioral cloning.
그래서 이것이 행동 복제의 전형적인 문제입니다.
So that's why, oftentimes, when people
그래서 사람들이 모방 학습을
are trying to make imitation learning work,
작동시키려고 할 때, 종종
people will follow this type of pipeline, where, on the top,
전문가가 수집한 시연이 맨 위에 있는
we have the demonstration collected by the experts.
이러한 유형의 파이프라인을 따릅니다.
Then we'll use that as a training data to do supervised
그런 다음 우리는 그것을 훈련 데이터로 사용하여 감독 학습을
learning to train this policy.
통해 이 정책을 훈련합니다.
And we'll rule out the policy in the real environment
그리고 우리는 실제 환경에서 정책을
and observe those failure cases.
실행하고 실패 사례를 관찰합니다.
And we either collect additional data
그리고 우리는 추가 데이터를
or provide corrective behaviors that
수집하거나 오류를
allows these data sets to not only contain
수정하는 행동을 제공하여
the initial demonstrations but also those corrective behaviors
이러한 데이터 세트가 초기 시연뿐만
that gets the errors from the policies back
아니라 오류를 표준 궤도로 되돌리는
to the canonical trajectory or get back to the trajectory.
수정 행동도 포함하도록 합니다.
They can still successfully accomplish the task.
그들은 여전히 성공적으로 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
So this is actually a typical life cycle.
그래서 이것은 실제 물리적 세계에서 모방 학습 에이전트나 알고리즘을 개발하려는 전형적인 생애 주기입니다.
We are trying to develop any imitation learning
그리고 이러한 맥락에서 사람들이 이러한
agents or imitation learning algorithms
종류의 모방 학습을 수행하면 실제로
in the real physical world.
작업이 무엇인지에 대한 명확한 정의가 없습니다.
And along these lines, because if people
작업은 이러한
do this kind of imitation learning,
시연 내에
there's not a very explicit definition
암묵적으로 숨겨져
of what the task actually is.
있습니다.
The task is implicitly hidden within those demonstrations.
그래서 역 강화 학습이라는 알고리즘 클래스가 있으며, 왼쪽은 사람들이 일반적으로 강화 학습에 대해 생각하는 것이고, 오른쪽은 사람들이 역 강화 학습을 사용하여 시연에서 보상을 요약하고 그 보상을 사용하여 일반적인 강화 학습을 수행하여 이러한 알고리즘을 배우려고 하는 것입니다.
So there's a class of algorithms called
초기 성공
inverse reinforcement learning, where on the left
사례 중 일부는
is what people typically think about for reinforcement
실제로 스탠포드에서
learning, whereas on the right, where people are trying
Pieter
to use this inverse reinforcement learning
Ab
to summarize the rewards from your demonstrations
beel과 Andrew
and be able to use that reward to do
Ng에 의해
typical reinforcement learning to learn
개발되
this kind of algorithms.
었습니다.
Some of the earlier success examples
그들은 헬리콥터를 제어하여
were actually also developed at Stanford
매우 미친 행동을
by Pieter Abbeel and also Andrew Ng.
수행할 수 있게 되었습니다.
It allows them to control helicopters to do some very,
그리고 이것은 실제로 매우 오래된
very crazy behaviors.
작업입니다.
And this is actually a very old work.
이러한 실제 물리적 헬리콥터에서 이러한 민첩하고 효과적인 행동을 달성할 수 있는 것은 그 당시 매우 인상적이었습니다.
And be able to achieve this type of agile and effective behaviors
그래서 이것은 시연에서 배우고 그 시연을
on these real physical helicopters
사용하여 보상을
is very impressive at that time.
요약하는 힘입니다.
So this is the power of learning from demonstrations
강화 학습과의 연결에서, 이것이 우리가
and using that demonstration to summarize the rewards.
달성할 수 있는 것입니다.
And in connections with reinforcement learning,
분명히, 수년 동안 사람들은 모방 학습 알고리즘을 점점 더
this is what we are able to achieve.
효과적으로 만들고 있으며, 특히 에너지 기반 모델과 연결하는 데 있어 그렇습니다.
So obviously, over the years, people
왼쪽에 표시된 명시적
have been making the imitation learning algorithms
정책을 배우는 대신, 그들은
more and more effective, especially
관찰에서 행동으로
in connecting with, for example, energy-based models.
직접 매핑을 수행합니다.
So instead of learning this kind of explicit policy shown
이러한 암묵적 정책을 생각해내면, 에너지 기반 모델에서 아이디어를 가져와
on the left, they directly do the mapping from the observation
관찰과 행동을 직접 사용하여 점수를 예측하고 이러한 에너지 기반 모델을 사용하여 추론하여
all through the actions.
예측된 행동 a를 얻을 수 있습니다.
If you are coming up with this kind of implicit policies,
이것은 로봇이
that takes the idea from energy-based models
매우 다중
that direct taking the observation and actions
모드의
to predict the score and using this kind of energy-based model
시연을 처리하거나 최적화
to do inference to get this kind of predicted actions a
경관이 매우 부드럽지
has allows the robots to handle demonstrations that
않을 수 있는 시나리오를
are very multi-modal or handle scenarios
처리할
where the optimization landscapes may not
수 있게
be very, very smooth.
합니다.
And the robot is able to come up with this kind of strategies,
로봇은 이러한 전략을 생각해내고
distill these policies from the demonstrations
시연에서 이러한 정책을 증류하여
in doing this kind of content-rich manipulation tasks.
콘텐츠가 풍부한 조작 작업을 수행합니다.
In order to say--
최근 로봇 학습의
some of the recent, very recent success
성공 중 일부는
of robot learning as a whole is the results of this work
확산 정책이라는 작업의 결과이며,
called diffusion policy, which, again, is also
이는 다시 생성 모델
taking some of the advances in the community
커뮤니티의 발전을
of generative models.
반영합니다.
For this one, for the implicit behavior cloning,
이 경우, 암묵적 행동 복제를 위해 사람들은
people are drawing inspiration from development
에너지 기반 모델의 개발에서 영감을
of energy-based model.
얻고 있습니다.
Energy-based model is a type of generative model developed
에너지 기반 모델은 딥 러닝 커뮤니티에서
in the deep learning community.
개발된 생성 모델의 일종입니다.
And there's another class of more powerful models
딥 러닝 커뮤니티에는 확산 모델이라고 불리는
in the deep learning community is called diffusion models.
더 강력한 모델의 또 다른 클래스가 있습니다.
And people are also trying to use the diffusion models to use
사람들은 또한 확산 모델을 정책 함수
it as a policy function class to allow the agents to also inherit
클래스로 사용하여 에이전트가 이러한 확산 모델의 이점과 특성을
the benefits and the properties from those diffusion models.
상속받도록 하려고 하고 있습니다.
So this work was originally done at Columbia.
이 작업은 원래 컬럼비아에서 수행되었습니다.
That's where I am right now.
제가 지금 있는 곳입니다.
And the leads, like the PI of this work, now come to Stanford.
이 작업의 주 연구자는 현재 스탠포드로 왔습니다.
You can see, many of the work I selected has a lot of roots
제가 선택한 많은 작업이 스탠포드에서 뿌리를 두고 있다는
here at Stanford.
것을 알 수 있습니다.
She is currently at the W departments at Stanford.
그녀는 현재 스탠포드의 W 부서에 있습니다.
And this policy really shows a very diverse set
이 정책은 로봇이 단순한 계획 추진뿐만
of capabilities, allow the robots
아니라 많은 세밀한 조작
to do not just planner pushing, but many fine-grained
작업을 수행할 수 있도록 매우 다양한 능력을
manipulation task.
보여줍니다.
Not only pick and place, but for example here,
단순한 집기와 놓기뿐만
spread butter on top of the spreads
아니라, 예를 들어 여기서
and also scrambled eggs, also peeling the potatoes
버터를 펴고 스크램블 에그를 만들고 감자를 껍질을 벗기고 책을
and sliding the books.
미는 작업도 포함됩니다.
So it really shows that this type
따라서 여러 가지 시연을
of recipe, where you collect a bunch of demonstrations
수집하고 최상의 정책과 학습 메커니즘을
and using the best policies, learning mechanisms,
사용하여 실제 물리적 세계에서 매우 효율적으로
you can get a policy that works in the real physical world
작동하는 정책을 얻을 수 있는 이러한 유형의 레시피가
in a very, very efficient manner, meaning you
정말로 보여줍니다. 즉, 아침에
collect the data in the morning.
데이터를 수집합니다.
You train the policy in the nuance.
정책을 미세하게 훈련합니다.
In the afternoon, you can have a working policy working
오후에는 실제 물리적 세계에서 작동하는 정책을
in the real physical world.
가질 수 있습니다.
So obviously, there's a lot of caveats
따라서 정책의 신뢰성과
in how reliable your policy is and how generalizable
일반화 가능성, 정책이 여전히
your policy is, how diversified the initial configuration can
매우 강력하게 작동할 수 있는 초기 구성의
be for the policy to still work very robustly.
다양성에 많은 주의사항이 있습니다.
But still, imitation learning is the most efficient way for you
하지만 여전히 모방 학습은 실제 물리적 세계에서 흥미로운
to get a policy that can do something
작업을 수행할 수 있는
interesting in the real physical world.
정책을 얻는 가장 효율적인 방법입니다.
And for the policies to be very effective and robust
정책이 실제 세계의 변동성에 매우 효과적이고
to the real-world variations, this type
강력하기 위해서는
of iterative data collections will
이러한 유형의 반복 데이터 수집이
need to be in place for the policy
필요하며, 정책이
to cover those kind of unexpected behaviors
예상치 못한 행동이나 어떤 종류의 이탈
or some kind of deviating behaviors.
행동을 포괄할 수 있어야 합니다.
So this is about imitation learning.
그래서 이것은 모방 학습에 관한 것입니다.
So any questions?
질문이 있습니까?
OK, so if there's no more questions,
좋습니다, 더 이상 질문이
I will use the remaining time to discuss
없다면 남은 시간을
some of the recent developments that
사용하여 로봇 학습에 대한 모든
drive all the craziness about robot learning, which
열광을 이끄는 최근 개발 사항인
is robotic foundation models.
로봇 기초 모델에 대해 논의하겠습니다.
And of course, this is a very involved domain.
물론, 이것은 매우 복잡한 분야입니다.
Actually, for each one of these items,
사실, 이러한 항목 각각에
you can actually have a course around them.
대해 강의를 진행할 수 있습니다.
So for today's lecture, I'm just skimming through them very,
그래서 오늘 강의에서는 매우 빠르게
very quickly.
훑어보겠습니다.
I only tell you the gist, the high-level knowledge
저는 여러분이 이러한 용어를 보면서 알아야
you need to get by looking at those terms.
할 핵심적인 내용, 고급 지식만을 말씀드리겠습니다.
And for robotic foundation models,
로봇 기초 모델은
it is a type of model that is very similar to reinforcement
기능 클래스에서 강화 학습이나 모방 학습과
learning or imitation learning in their function class.
매우 유사한 모델 유형입니다.
There's no explicit representation for them
이러한 모델의 상태에 대한
of the states or this kind of model.
명시적인 표현은 없습니다.
For example, this robotic foundation model
예를 들어, 이 로봇 기초
doesn't learn the model of the environments.
모델은 환경의 모델을 학습하지 않습니다.
It is still a policy that maps from the observation
여전히 관찰에서 행동으로
and goes into the actions.
매핑하는 정책입니다.
That's still like a representative--
이것은 여전히 대표적이며,
can be very nicely represented using these figures.
이러한 도형을 사용하여 매우 잘 표현될 수 있습니다.
So you have this agents, which is
현재 상태와 목표를
a policy that takes the current state
입력으로 받아들이는 정책인 이
and also the goal as inputs.
에이전트가 있습니다.
And you're trying to generate these actions that
그리고 여러분은 실제 물리적 세계에서
can be executed in the real physical world.
실행할 수 있는 이러한 행동을 생성하려고 합니다.
But you might say that this is very
하지만 이것이 모방 학습 및
similar to imitation learning and reinforcement learning.
강화 학습과 매우 유사하다고 말할 수 있습니다.
So what's special about this robotic foundation models?
이 로봇 기초 모델의 특별한 점은 무엇인가요?
So this is actually all rooted back
이는 사실 기초 모델
to all the developments within the foundation model domain,
분야 내의 모든 발전에 뿌리를 두고 있으며,
especially those language-related foundation
특히 언어 관련 기초
model and also those vision
모델과 비전 언어 관련 기초 모델을
models, meaning it is a policy.
의미합니다. 이는 정책입니다.
But it needs to generalize much better than a policy that just
하지만 이는 특정 작업에만 적용되는 정책보다
works for one specific task.
훨씬 더 잘 일반화되어야 합니다.
Here is actually my definitions.
여기 제 정의가 있습니다.
I'm drawing analogies from the current developments of vision
저는 비전 언어 모델의 현재 발전에서 비유를
language models, meaning their outputs may not always
끌어오고 있습니다. 이는 그들의 출력이 항상 완벽하지는
be the perfect one, but it will always
않지만, 이 기초 모델을 통해
generate something reasonable as you prompts
합리적인 무언가를 항상 생성할
this kind of foundation model.
것이라는 의미입니다.
So what we hope to achieve with this robotic foundation model
우리가 이 로봇 기초 모델로 달성하고자 하는
is the synthesized action may not always
것은, 합성된 행동이 관찰과 작업에
be the optimal actions as conditioned
의해 조건지어진 최적의 행동이 아닐
by the observation and the task.
수 있다는 것입니다.
But the general trajectory will always
하지만 일반적인 궤적은 항상
be beautiful and reasonable to execute
아름답고 실제 물리적 세계에서
in the real physical world.
실행하기에 합리적일 것입니다.
Beautiful meaning you shouldn't use any jiggling motions.
아름답다는 것은 흔들리는 동작을 사용하지 말라는 의미입니다.
It should be smooth and continuous.
부드럽고 연속적이어야 합니다.
Reasonable meaning you should listen to the language
합리적이라는 것은 로봇에게 주어진
instructions you are given to the robots.
언어 지침을 들어야 한다는 의미입니다.
So obviously, there are also many different names describing
따라서 분명히 같은 것을 설명하는 다양한
exactly the same things.
이름이 존재합니다.
Some people call it Vision Language Action
어떤 사람들은 이를 비전 언어 행동
Models like VLAs.
모델(VLAs)이라고 부릅니다.
Some people call it large behavior models.
어떤 사람들은 이를 대규모 행동 모델이라고 부릅니다.
But in the essence, they are all describing the same thing,
하지만 본질적으로 그들은 모두 같은 것을 설명하고
meaning this policy, taking the observation and language
있으며, 이는 관찰과 언어 지침 또는 작업
instructions or whatever, like a task specification.
사양을 받아들이는 정책을 의미합니다.
You're trying to generate the actions that generalize widely
당신은 다양한 시나리오에 걸쳐
across a wide range of scenarios.
널리 일반화되는 행동을 생성하려고 합니다.
So this area is actually quite noisy.
이 분야는 사실 꽤 시끄럽습니다.
Noisy meaning it's very, very hard
시끄럽다는 것은 다양한 종류의
to quantify the progress of different kinds
로봇 기초 모델의 진행 상황을 정량화하기 매우
of robotic foundation models.
어렵다는 의미입니다.
Because you're calling it foundation model,
당신이 이를 기초 모델이라고 부르고 있다면, 그것은
what does that mean?
무엇을 의미하나요?
That means you expect this model to generalize very broadly
그것은 이 모델이 다양한 시나리오에 걸쳐 매우 널리 일반화되기를
over a wide range of scenarios.
기대한다는 것을 의미합니다.
If that's your expectation, you actually
그것이 당신의 기대라면, 실제로 널리
need significant evidence to show it actually
일반화된다는 것을 보여줄 상당한
generalizes broadly.
증거가 필요합니다.
So that's why evaluation and quantitative measurements
그래서 그들의 진행 상황에 대한 평가와 정량적
of their progress is very challenging.
측정이 매우 도전적입니다.
But still, by looking at their empirical videos,
하지만 여전히 그들의 경험적 비디오를 보면
you can still see a lot of very interesting and concrete
지난 2년 동안 매우 흥미롭고 구체적인
progress over the past two years.
진행 상황을 많이 볼 수 있습니다.
So a lot of the earlier investigation
많은 초기 조사는
starts with RT-1, which was released
2022년 12월에 출시된
in the December of 2022.
RT-1에서 시작됩니다.
And since then, I would say maybe roughly every half a year,
그 이후로, 대략 매 반년마다 새로운 모델이 등장한다고 할
there's a new model, for example, RT-2, RT-X, OpenVLA,
수 있습니다. 예를 들어 RT-2, RT-X,
and some of the recent ones like Pi-Zero,
OpenVLA, 최근의 Pi-Zero와 같은
that is making concrete progress along these lines of developing
모델들이 더 일반화 가능한 로봇 기초 모델을 개발하는
more and more generalizable robotic foundation models.
방향으로 구체적인 진전을 이루고 있습니다.
And actually, this year, there's a boost.
실제로 올해는 큰 발전이 있었습니다.
There's a [INAUDIBLE] first of a lot of foundation models,
많은 기초 모델의 첫 번째 부스트가 있었으며, Helix, Hi-Robot,
like Helix, Hi-Robot, Gemini Robotics, Pi-0.5, et cetera.
Gemini Robotics, Pi-0.5 등이 포함됩니다.
So there's a lot of investigations
이 분야에는 자본
and also investments in this domain
투자뿐만 아니라 더
in not only like a capital investment
나은, 더 나은, 더 일반화 가능한
but talent investments in developing better, better,
로봇 기초 모델을 개발하기 위한
and better and more generalizable
인재 투자도 많이
robotic foundation models.
이루어지고 있습니다.
So due to the time, I clearly cannot go into the details
시간 관계상 이 모든 모델의 세부 사항에 대해 자세히
of all these models.
설명할 수는 없습니다.
So if you are interested, I actually
그래서 관심이 있으시다면,
gave a tutorial two months ago at [INAUDIBLE],
두 달 전에 [INAUDIBLE]에서 이
specifically describing and discussing some
축을 따라 몇 가지 모델을 구체적으로 설명하고
of the models along this axis.
논의하는 튜토리얼을 진행했습니다.
If you are interested, please go and watch it.
관심이 있으시면 꼭 시청해 주세요.
And for today, I'll be mostly giving you a high-level overview
오늘은 이러한 기초 모델에 실제로 필수적인 것이
of what actually is essential for this kind of foundation
무엇인지, 그리고 Pi-Zero의 예를 통해
models and what it actually looks like, with any examples
그것이 실제로 어떻게 생겼는지에 대한 고급
from Pi-Zero.
개요를 주로 제공할 것입니다.
So Pi-Zero was first released in October 2024.
Pi-Zero는 2024년 10월에 처음 출시되었습니다.
I think this is the word that convinced me
이 단어가 이 유형의 로봇 기초 모델이
that this type of robotic foundation model
실제 환경에서 매우 신뢰할
can do some very reliable dexterous manipulations
수 있는 섬세한 조작을 할 수 있다는 것을 저를
in the real-world environments.
설득시켰다고 생각합니다.
It can handle cloth folding and box
이 모델은 신뢰할 수 있는
folding and many other different types of manipulation tasks
방식으로 옷 접기, 상자 접기 및 다양한 조작
at a very reliable manner.
작업을 처리할 수 있습니다.
And here is how the framework actually
여기서 프레임워크의 전반적인
looks like on the high level.
모습이 어떻게 생겼는지 보여줍니다.
On the left is data sets.
왼쪽은 데이터 세트입니다.
So for any model to be called the foundation model,
어떤 모델이 기초 모델이라고 불리려면 그 기초
it needs a fuel for that foundation model.
모델을 위한 연료가 필요합니다.
And that fuel is data.
그 연료는 데이터입니다.
So they aggregate a lot of data both within academia
그들은 학계 내에서 수집한 데이터와 여러
and also data collected by themselves
다른 구현을 통해 스스로 수집한
across many different embodiments,
많은 데이터를 집계하여 로봇이
where the robot is doing some kind
실제 환경에서 흥미롭고
of interesting and useful task in the real-world environments.
유용한 작업을 수행하는 데이터를 모았습니다.
And they use this data to do pre-training.
그리고 이 데이터를 사용하여 사전 훈련을 수행합니다.
And one important caveats of this pre-training
이 사전 훈련의
is this starts with a pre-trained visual language
중요한 주의사항 중 하나는 이미
model, the vision language model that's
방대한 양의
already trained on vast amount of vision-language-related data
비전-언어 관련 데이터로 훈련된 사전 훈련된
that can naturally adapt those kind of semantically knowledge
시각 언어 모델로 시작한다는
from those models.
것입니다.
And together, by doing code fine-tuning, what
그리고 함께 코드 미세 조정을 수행함으로써,
they call code fine-tuning, using both objective for action
그들이 코드 미세 조정이라고 부르는 것을
predictions and also the objective adapted
통해, 행동 예측을 위한 목표와 이러한
from those vision question answering those type of tasks,
비전 질문 응답 작업에서 적응된 목표를
you will be able to first preserve the semantic knowledge
사용하여, 모델 내의 의미적 지식을 보존할
within those models.
수 있습니다.
But at the same time, you can predict the robot actions.
하지만 동시에 로봇의 행동을 예측할 수 있습니다.
And this is the pre-training stage.
이것이 사전 훈련 단계입니다.
A very important design for many of the existing robotic
기존의 많은 로봇 기초 모델에 대한 매우
foundation models is called post-training,
중요한 설계는 포스트 훈련이라고
which is also inspired by many of the developments
불리며, 이는 대형 언어 모델
in the large language model communities
커뮤니티의 많은 발전에서
where you have this base model.
영감을 받았습니다.
Base model can give you some reasonable baseline performance.
기본 모델은 합리적인 기준 성능을 제공합니다.
But if you really want the performance to be very, very
하지만 특정 작업에서 성능이 매우
good on a specific task, you actually
좋기를 원한다면, 실제로는
have to collect task-specific data to fine-tune the models,
모델을 미세 조정하기 위해 작업 특정 데이터를 수집해야
do post-training on the data for that specific task
하며, 그 특정 작업에 대한 데이터로 포스트
for the performance to be satisfied.
훈련을 수행해야 성능이 만족스러워집니다.
So they are evaluating their whole systems
그래서 그들은 세 가지 다른 범주에서
over three different categories.
전체 시스템을 평가하고 있습니다.
The first one is directly using their base model.
첫 번째는 그들의 기본 모델을 직접 사용하는 것입니다.
And their base model can already be good enough
그들의 기본 모델은 이미 매우
for some very simple in-distribution data.
간단한 분포 내 데이터에 대해 충분히 좋을 수 있습니다.
The task is actually the task that
이 작업은 실제로 사전 훈련
might have already been encountered
단계에서 이미
during the pre-training stage.
접했을 수 있는 작업입니다.
For different task but slightly more complicated,
조금 더 복잡한 다른 작업의 경우,
you can do post-training to allow the base
기본 모델이 이러한 분포 내 작업에서
model to further improve on those in-distribution tasks.
더 개선될 수 있도록 후속 훈련을 할 수 있습니다.
And for unseen task, typically you
보지 못한 작업의 경우,
have to do post-training by collecting
일반적으로 해당 작업에 특화된
those task-specific data and fine-tune your pre-trained model
데이터를 수집하고 이러한 작업에 대해 사전 훈련된
on these tasks for you to be performance.
모델을 미세 조정하여 성능을 높여야 합니다.
And this Pi-Zero model is actually open sourced.
그리고 이 Pi-Zero 모델은 실제로 오픈 소스입니다.
And you can just download the checkpoints.
체크포인트를 다운로드할 수 있습니다.
The students in my lab have already
내 연구실의 학생들은 이미
been starting to play with their models
그들의 모델로 실험을 시작하고 후속 훈련을
and trying to do post-training.
시도하고 있습니다.
And we're starting to see some very promising results.
그리고 우리는 매우 유망한 결과를 보기 시작했습니다.
So if you are interested, I highly encourage you to try it.
그래서 관심이 있다면, 시도해 보시기를 강력히 권장합니다.
That is a very good question.
정말 좋은 질문입니다.
So you are essentially asking about the efficiency
기존 로봇 기초 모델의 효율성에
of the existing robotic foundation models.
대해 질문하고 계신 것입니다.
So there's a lot of reasons why the policy is actually
정책이 실제로 인간보다 느린 이유는 여러
slower than humans.
가지가 있습니다.
One of the major reasons is actually adapted
주요 이유 중 하나는 데이터 수집
from how the data was collected, how the demonstration
방식, 즉 시연 데이터 수집 방식에서
data was collected.
기인합니다.
Typically, for many of these scenarios,
일반적으로 이러한
the demonstration data was collected
시나리오의
by human teleoperating the robots on that exact same robots
경우, 시연 데이터는 로봇을
to do the data collection in, for example, folding this box.
원격 조작하여 수집되었습니다.
And human teleoperations is actually
그리고 인간의 원격 조작은
slower than humans just using their hands to do these tasks,
인간이 손으로 이러한 작업을 수행하는 것보다 느립니다,
even if you have gone through hours of training.
비록 몇 시간의 훈련을 받았더라도.
This is because you are just using a different embodiment
이는 당신이 가장 익숙한
than an embodiment that you person is the most familiar with
구현체와 다른 구현체를 사용하고 있으며, 동시에
and, also at the same time, because the robot arms are still
로봇 팔이 당신과 일정 거리를 두고
a certain distance away from you.
있기 때문입니다.
There will be occlusion.
차폐가 발생할 것입니다.
Sometimes, you have to look very closely, carefully,
때때로, 정말로 이해하기 위해서는 매우 가까이,
like changing your heads, changing the viewing
조심스럽게 바라봐야 하며, 머리를 바꾸거나 시각 각도를
angles in order to really understand,
바꿔야 할 수도 있습니다.
is it the time to progress into the next task stage or not?
다음 작업 단계로 진행할 시간인지 아닌지를 판단하기 위해서입니다.
There's a lot of caveats and inefficiencies
현재 데이터 수집 방식에는 많은
of the current data collection regimes.
주의사항과 비효율성이 있습니다.
That is why the policy directly trained on those data
그래서 이러한 데이터에 직접 훈련된
turned out to be slower than the human speeds.
정책이 인간의 속도보다 느리게 나타났습니다.
So that's why there's a lot of investigations
그래서 우리는 이러한 데이터 수집을 더
in how we can do those kind of data collections
효율적으로, 인간의 속도로 수행할 수
to be even more efficient, to be at human speeds.
있는 방법에 대한 많은 조사가 이루어지고 있습니다.
That is actually a very active research direction.
이는 실제로 매우 활발한 연구 방향입니다.
So this is a very good question.
그래서 이것은 매우 좋은 질문입니다.
So for this box folding task, I would
이 상자 접기 작업에 대해, 저는 이것이
argue this is already a very long horizon task.
이미 매우 긴 수평 작업이라고 주장할 것입니다.
So I was very impressed by how good this one single policy is
저는 이 단일 정책이 이 긴 수평 작업을 얼마나 잘 처리할 수
able to handle this long horizon task.
있는지에 매우 감명받았습니다.
But you could argue, if you really
하지만 만약 이 정책이 더
want this policy to be useful in a more larger scale,
큰 규모, 즉 그들의 야외 시나리오나 집에서 유용하게
like in the wild scenarios for them, in your home,
사용되기를 원한다면, 로봇이 상자만
you not only want the robot to fold the box.
접는 것이 아니라는 점을 주장할 수 있습니다.
You want it to fold the shirts and clean the beds
셔츠를 접고 침대를 정리하며 바닥의
and clean all the messes on the floor.
모든 엉망을 치우기를 원합니다.
If in those type of scenarios--
이러한 유형의 시나리오에서는 현재
currently, me, personally, I don't
개인적으로 저는 하나의 거대한
believe one gigantic policy is able to adapt
정책이 이러한 시나리오에 적응할 수 있다고
to those scenarios.
믿지 않습니다.
Some higher-level abstractions or some kind
더 높은 수준의
of scene graph, some symbolic representations
추상화나 어떤 종류의
needs to be in place as a condition for this vision
장면 그래프, 상징적 표현이 이러한 정책이
language action models for those policy
다양한 작업으로 유도되고
to be the most effective and useful to steer
더 큰 환경과 더 복잡한
into different type of tasks and scale
작업으로 확장될 수
to larger-scale environments and more complicated tasks.
있도록 하기 위한 조건으로 필요합니다.
So this started with a pre-trained vision language
그래서 이는 사전 훈련된 비전 언어 모델로
model.
시작되었습니다.
So that's why there's already a lot of semantic knowledge
그래서 이미 이 비전 언어 데이터를 사용한
that are learned through this large-scale pre-training using
대규모 사전 훈련을 통해 많은 의미적
this vision language data.
지식이 학습되었습니다.
So that is why some of the generalization
그래서 일부 일반화가 무료로 발생하는
are coming for free, meaning the base model can actually
이유는 기본 모델이 의미적 수준에서
have surprisingly good levels of generalization
놀라울 정도로 좋은 일반화 수준을 가질
at the semantic level.
수 있기 때문입니다.
And I just have to fine-tune this model with those robot data
그리고 저는 이 모델을 로봇 데이터로 미세 조정해야
to make sure it can also generalize
하며, 이는 의미적 수준뿐만
not as a semantic level but also as an action level.
아니라 행동 수준에서도 일반화할 수 있도록 하기 위해서입니다.
So we can have the question maybe at the end
질문은 아마도 끝에 할 수 있을 것입니다.
because we are already about time.
이미 시간이 다 되어가고 있습니다.
I still have maybe one--
아직도 마지막으로
the last, maybe, two, three minutes,
두세 분 정도 남았으니,
I will discuss some of the remaining challenges,
로봇 학습 모델 개발과 관련된
especially along the development of robot learning models.
남은 도전 과제에 대해 논의하겠습니다.
So one of the major challenges the whole community recognizes
전체 커뮤니티가 인식하는 주요 도전 과제 중
is evaluation.
하나는 평가입니다.
Evaluation currently is primarily
현재 평가는 주로 실제
done in the real world.
세계에서 이루어집니다.
For example, this is a picture of a Google Robotics.
예를 들어, 이것은 구글 로보틱스의 사진입니다.
They have a grid of this kind of teleoperating Aloha systems
그들은 데이터 수집과 평가를 수행하는 이러한 종류의
that they are doing data collection and also evaluation.
원격 조작 Aloha 시스템의 그리드를 가지고 있습니다.
And real-world evaluation is both costly and noisy.
실제 세계에서의 평가는 비용이 많이 들고 소음이 많습니다.
Their exact words to me was, for evaluation, they
그들이 저에게 한 정확한 말은, 평가를 위해 그들은 여전히 진전을
have large enough budget such that they can still
이룰 수 있을 만큼 충분한 예산을 가지고 있다는
make progress.
것이었습니다.
This was their exact words, meaning
이것은 그들의 정확한 말로,
if you were to do the evaluation or I were to do the evaluation,
만약 당신이 평가를 하거나 제가 평가를
the results can be very different from each other,
한다면, 초기 구성과 조명 조건이 어떻게
depending on how we specify the initial configuration
변할지에 따라 결과가 매우 다를
and how the lighting condition might change.
수 있다는 것을 의미합니다.
Even the friction parameters of any factor
어떤 요소의 마찰 매개변수조차도
can make a huge difference in how robust
다운스트림 정책의 강건성에 큰 차이를
your downstream policy is.
만들 수 있습니다.
So this is very costly, and they have
그래서 이것은 매우 비용이 많이
to wait for two days for the results to come back.
들며, 그들은 결과가 돌아오기를 위해 이틀을 기다려야 합니다.
And currently, there's very weak correlation
현재 훈련 손실과 실제 세계 성공률 간의
between the training loss and real-world success rates.
상관관계는 매우 약합니다.
So this is another very important caveat and difference
그래서 이것은 감독 학습과 이와 같은
between supervised learning and also
순차적 의사 결정, 이
this kind of sequential decision making,
정책 학습 간의 또 다른
this kind of policy learning is, for supervised learning,
매우 중요한 주의사항과 차이점입니다. 감독
your training loss directly measures how good your model is.
학습에서는 훈련 손실이 모델의 성능을 직접 측정합니다.
But for this kind of policy learning,
하지만 이 정책
your training loss measures how good this one-step prediction
학습에서는 훈련 손실이 이 일단계 예측의 성능을
is, which sometimes may not be and, actually,
측정하며, 이는 때때로 그렇지 않을 수
oftentimes is not indicative of the performance of policy
있고, 실제로는 종종 긴 작업 수평에서 정책의
over long task horizons, even if your loss is low.
성능을 나타내지 않습니다, 비록 손실이 낮더라도.
But for long horizon task execution,
하지만 긴 시간 동안의 작업
your policy can actually be worse.
실행에서는 정책이 실제로 더 나쁠 수 있습니다.
And the training objective versus the task-specific metrics
훈련 목표와 작업별 지표, 예를 들어
like training versus test horizons
훈련과 테스트 수평선 간의
are some of the reasons explaining
차이 등이 정책 성능을
why it is very hard to come up with even
측정하기 위한 근사적 지표를
approximate or approximate metrics
제시하기 어렵게 만드는
to measure the performance of the policy.
이유 중 일부입니다.
And people have to rely on real-world evaluations.
사람들은 실제 평가에 의존해야 합니다.
So then the question is, what about
그렇다면 시뮬레이션 환경에서
doing the evaluation in the simulated environments?
평가를 수행하는 것은 어떨까요?
There has been a lot of investigation,
예를 들어, 스탠포드의
for example, of behavior, which is
물리 실험실과 메타의
done in physics lab here also at Stanford
Habitat 3.0에서 수행된 행동에
and also the Habitat 3.0 from Meta.
대한 많은 연구가 있었습니다.
Now, people are trying to come up
현재 사람들은 이러한
with this expensive simulated environments,
비싼 시뮬레이션 환경을 만들어
trying to do evaluation and measurements of the robot
로봇 정책의 평가와 측정을 시도하고
policies.
있습니다.
And obviously, there has their own issues,
그리고 분명히, 시뮬레이션과 실제 간의 격차와
especially with regard to sim-to-real gap.
관련하여 그들만의 문제가 있습니다.
How can you do very accurate simulation of rigid body,
강체, 변형 가능한 물체, 의류의 매우 정확한 시뮬레이션을
deformable object, and clothes?
어떻게 수행할 수 있을까요?
They have good correlations with the real-world performance.
그들은 실제 성능과 좋은 상관관계를 가지고 있습니다.
And asset is also another major issue,
자산도 또 다른 주요 문제로,
where large-scale generalizations and generations
대규모 일반화 및 자산
of those assets is a huge pain.
생성이 큰 어려움입니다.
I can elaborate but maybe after the lectures.
자세히 설명할 수 있지만, 아마도 강의 후에 하겠습니다.
And also, how do you digitize the real world is an issue.
그리고 실제 세계를 디지털화하는 방법도 문제입니다.
And how to do procedural generations
현실적이고 다양한 것들의
of realistic and diverse things are all issues
절차적 생성을 수행하는 방법은 로봇
of using simulation to do evaluations for robot learning
학습 정책을 평가하기 위해 시뮬레이션을 사용하는
policies.
모든 문제입니다.
And really, when you find the correlation between sim and real
그리고 실제와 시뮬레이션 간의 상관관계를
and it's calling upon the ImageNet in Embodied AI,
발견했을 때, 이는 Embodied AI의 ImageNet을
the reason why ImageNet was successful
호출하게 되며, ImageNet이 성공한
is because, at least for a few years, any progress in ImageNet,
이유는 적어도 몇 년 동안 ImageNet의 모든 진전이
meaning progress in deep learning and computer vision,
심층 학습과 컴퓨터 비전의 진전을
we want the same thing.
의미했기 때문입니다.
We want to have this platform, meaning
우리는 이 플랫폼을 원합니다.
any progress on that benchmark or platform,
즉, 그 기준선이나 플랫폼에서의 모든 진전은
meaning progress in robot learnings.
로봇 학습의 진전을 의미합니다.
So that's something that we really want.
그래서 우리가 정말로 원하는 것입니다.
And I can maybe skip through.
그리고 저는 아마도 건너뛰어도 될 것 같습니다.
We talk about how to build this foundational policies that
우리는 이러한 기초 정책을 구축하는 방법과
can also be investigations on how to build
기초 세계 모델을 구축하는 방법에
a foundational world model.
대한 조사를 이야기합니다.
Especially, now, people are collecting
특히 지금, 사람들은 이 기초
large-scale, action-conditioned robot interaction
정책을 훈련하기 위해 대규모의 행동 조건
data to train this foundation policy.
로봇 상호작용 데이터를 수집하고 있습니다.
But there's a lot of dynamics knowledge
하지만 그 데이터에는 많은 동역학
embedded in those data.
지식이 내재되어 있습니다.
If we just use those data to do policy learning,
그 데이터를 정책 학습에만 사용한다면, 정말
that would be such a waste.
아쉬운 일이 될 것입니다.
So we are also thinking about how can we
그래서 우리는 이미 수집된 이
use this large-scale, action-conditioned robot
대규모 행동 조건 로봇 상호작용
interaction data that was already collected
데이터를 어떻게 활용하여 기초 정책을
to train those foundational policy to train
훈련하고 기초 세계 모델을 훈련할 수
this foundational world model and how they can do interplay
있을지, 그리고 서로 어떻게 상호작용할 수 있을지를
between each other.
고민하고 있습니다.
And there are some existing works
그리고 이러한 기초
that are thinking about along the direction of building
세계 모델을 구축하는 방향에 대해 생각하는
this kind of foundational world models.
기존 연구들이 있습니다.
And there's some very interesting characteristics you
그리고 당신이 생각할 수 있는 매우 흥미로운 특성들이 있습니다.
might think about, like do you want it to be 3D?
예를 들어, 3D로 만들고 싶으신가요?
Do you want structural prior?
구조적 우선순위를 원하나요?
How much learning versus how much physics?
얼마나 학습하고 얼마나 물리학을 적용할 것인가?
And how you can correlate with the real physical world.
그리고 실제 물리적 세계와 어떻게 상관관계를 맺을 수 있을까요?
And maybe, actually, I think we are about time.
그리고 아마도, 실제로 우리는 시간이 다 되어가는 것 같습니다.
So I will end it here.
그래서 여기서 마치겠습니다.
And this is the future we hope to achieve to really build
그리고 이것이 우리가 달성하고자 하는 미래로, 매우
this foundational robotic model that can work very widely
널리 작동하고 비구조적 데이터 환경에서 잘
and generalize very well in the unstructured data
일반화할 수 있는 기초 로봇 모델을
environments around us.
구축하는 것입니다.
And next lectures will be human-centered AI.
다음 강의는 인간 중심 AI가 될 것입니다.
And that will be the end of today's lecture.
그리고 오늘 강의는 여기서 마치겠습니다.
Thank you so much.
정말 감사합니다.